Questions from members, and we have read your submission. But over to you.
Thank you. Kia ora koutou.
I'm a lawyer based in Nelson.
And so I want to make a couple of points in my oral
submission. The first is that, contrary to
suggestions I've seen in some quarters,
the Supreme Court's decision here is not a novel
one. The tort of public nuisance is an old
area of law.
It's been applied to
environmental issues in the past.
There are a bunch of cases in Victorian
times on water pollution
arising from industrialization.
And the cases were quite clear that the fact that you're only
contributing maybe a limited amount to the pollution, and there'd still be
pollution if you just took away your individual contributions, that
isn't a barrier to being found liable for public
nuisance. So actually, in my view, the court's decision was quite orthodox in just
applying old principles of law to a new
context.
So I think that that's something to bear in mind when it comes to whether
it's justifiable to
legislate to override this court
decision on this old area of law,
when we're talking about one of the greatest challenges we
face as a planet and as
humanity.
The other thing I'd like to say is around the retrospective nature of the
legislation. And in this case, it's not just
retrospectively taking away people's
right to sue and to get a remedy for public nuisance.
It's also interfering with
existing court proceedings, court proceedings
that are currently in existence
and before the courts. Even when Parliament
legislates retrospectively,
it normally excludes proceedings
that are already before the courts.
That's because
while retrospective legislation, of course, always raises issues in
terms of the rule of law, but there are particularly grave issues in terms of the
rule of law and separation of powers when you're interfering with
court cases that are in existence before the courts.
And so that's the points that I want to make.
Thank you very much. We've got a question from Dr. Deborah Russell.
Thank you, Chair. Thank you, Daniel.
Would you see a problem with Parliament legislating after the
completion of Mike Smith's case?
Well, I think that would be
a better way to do it. If you
felt, after the outcome of that case, that
legislation was necessary, of course, Parliament could legislate.
But then it would know what it's actually legislating to,
what the actual issue is with the law.
Because at the moment, all the Supreme Court said is, "Well, this case can
go forward to trial, and we can have a full judgment.
It's not untenable."
But we don't know whether it will succeed or not.
We don't know what the law will look like at the end of that.
And actually, interfering with pending
cases before the courts is a pretty extraordinary step for
Parliament to take.
Thank you.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Daniel. Nice to see you again.
And thank you both for your written and your oral submission. We appreciate it.
Thanks.
Okay, members, we now come to Lawyers for Climate
Action. And
let's just see who we have got here. We've got Jennie.
And who else is going to be with you, Jennie, or is it just yourself?
Laura McKay. So I don't know whether she's able to be on screen at
the same time, but I can hand over to her when I'm finished.
That might be-
Okay. We do have Laura on here, so
up to you.
Jennie, you've got 10 minutes. We have read your written submission.
But please do leave some time at the end for questions. Over to you.
Thank you. We'll try to do that. Well, kia ora koutou.
My name is Jennie Cooper. I'm here in my capacity as president of Lawyers for
Climate Action. And as we were just mentioning, I'm here together with
our acting executive director, Laura McKay.
So Lawyers for Climate Action NZ is opposed to the bill.
We say it's a disproportionate knee-jerk reaction to one
case which has yet to be decided.
It goes against the interests of every single person in New Zealand except
the major emitters who lobbied for it.
The reason we say that is because everyone suffers the consequences of
climate change,
such as the damage caused by extreme weather events and sea level rise.
But based on this bill, everyone will be left paying for those
consequences without any opportunity to seek redress from those
most responsible.
It is bad law based on bad policy, and it's the result
of a deeply flawed decision-making process.
I'd like to start with a few comments on the process.
First of all, the bill does appear to be a direct response to secret
lobbying by Z Energy and Fonterra.
It would appear that at their request, the government is seeking to step in to
decide private litigation in favor of powerful corporate
interests.
Now, whatever you think about Mr. Smith's claim, whatever you think about the role
of tort law should be in relation to climate change, that sets a
dangerous precedent. This bill is an infringement of the rights of Mr.
Smith, and it is also directly contrary to the rule of law.
Secondly, the process for the introduction of this bill has been
unacceptably rushed. There's been no proper consultation, including no
consultation with Maori, and the opportunity for public debate has been
seriously curtailed. Setting a 10-day submission period
closing at 9:00 a.m. after a long weekend sends a clear message that
the proponents of this bill have no real interest in public feedback,
despite this being a vitally important issue of public interest.
So we say that's a serious concern, because this bill not only takes away Mr.
Smith's claim, but it would effectively impose a total restriction on
anyone's ability to bring a claim for damages caused by any event where
climate change is a contributing factor, and I'll come back to that, but it does
appear that the implications of this don't appear to have been recognized or
thought through. And we say that this rushed process is
completely unnecessary. Mr. Smith's claim has been on foot since
2000. There has been adequate time to consider its
implications. The Supreme Court decision saying it should go to trial was issued
two years ago. There's no good reason why this issue is now being
addressed with urgency.
Should I pause for questions? I do have more points to make.
What is the procedure?
Make all the points and then we'll have the questions at the end.
Great. Thank you.
Turning to why it's bad policy. Well, first of all, the stated
reason for the bill is to avoid the risk of a parallel regime to the Climate Change
Response Act. There is no such risk for the reasons that the Supreme
Court held, which is that the Climate Change Response Act does not address
issues of compensation, liability for harm,
and redress the issues that Mr. Smith's claim raises and the
issues which tort law addresses. So there's nothing in
the act that addresses those issues or that will be contradicted by that.
There is nothing in legislation that deals with the question of who is
able to claim for compensation and who is liable to pay for compensation
for the harm caused by climate change, which includes harm from
weather-related events such as floods,
droughts, slips, storms, and fires, which we are seeing with increasing
regularity.
Now, who can claim and who should pay for these losses are difficult and
complex questions.
It's very arguable that they should be addressed by legislation, but
we do not have any legislation that addresses that.
Rather than developing suitable legislation to fill this gap, this
bill simply says that there is no accountability for major emitters
and no way for those suffering from climate harm to seek
redress. Secondly, the bill is said to be
aimed at ensuring certainty for business.
We say it will have the opposite effect, and Laura will touch on that
briefly as well.
Finally, from me, why the bill is bad law.
It's clear the drafting process has been rushed.
The scope of the bill is extraordinarily wide and likely to have unintended
consequences. For example, it protects emitters from
liability for any damage to the extent that it was or may
have been, in whole or in part, directly or indirectly
caused or contributed to by climate change.
In effect, that means that anyone who contributes to climate change
cannot be sued for any damage caused in New Zealand by
any extreme weather-related event, such as a storm, a
flood, et cetera, because all of those events will have
been at least partly contributed to by climate change.
Now, this bar appears to apply
regardless of whether the person to be sued's emissions
are the reason they are being sued or some other reason.
So for example, if an emitter of greenhouse gases
also negligently fails to maintain a stop bank or fails to
remove forestry slash and thereby causes a risk of damage to the
neighbor's property, based on the wording of this bill, they won't be able
to be sued for the damage that may cause if a severe weather event
is also a contributing factor to the damage.
And I don't believe any consideration has been given to the consequences of that.
Finally from me, before I hand over to Laura,
I would ask the members of this committee to step back
and reflect on the fact that the bill before them would
explicitly protect emitters everywhere in the world from
any form of liability to anyone in New Zealand
for, quote, "Threats to the continuation of a safe
and habitable climate system."
Ask yourselves whose interests such a law would serve and how it
could possibly be justified in the public interest.
Thank you, and I'll hand over to Laura.
Thanks, Jenny.
Kia ora, Jenny.
So there's three more key impacts of the bill I'd like to note.
Those relate to the inconsistency of the bill with the Treaty of Waitangi, also
with the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act, and also with New Zealand's international
obligations. Not going to go through our submission, but I do want to highlight a
few key points. So first relating to the Treaty of Waitangi.
In addition to the point that Jenny's already made about the rushed and inadequate
process, it's important to note that at least according to the regulatory impact
statement, there's been no consultation with Maori.
That regulatory impact statement itself acknowledges that this is likely
inconsistent with the Crown's Treaty of Waitangi obligations.
The Crown's provided no good reason for rushing through this bill and no good
reason why it's failed to engage with Maori on a bill with such significant impact.
I think that's particularly important to note in light of the lobbying for this
bill from some of the defendants in the Smith and Ponteria case.
As noted in our submissions, if this bill is to proceed, then at a very minimum,
a full consultation process should be undertaken, and particularly with Maori.
Secondly, in relation to the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act, we've set out in our
submission some of the minimum rights that the bill undermines, but one in
particular I want to highlight.
Under Section 8 of the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act, no one shall be deprived of
life except on such grounds as are established by law and are consistent with the
principles of fundamental justice.
So as noted in our submission, the courts have been steadily developing an
understanding of climate change as a threat to the right of life But in
this case, the right to life is actually explicitly recognized in the bill
because it bars a range of emissions related climate change effects,
including endangering or impairing the life, safety,
health, property, or comfort of the public.
It's really difficult to understand why unproven concerns about certainty
for business would be prioritized over the right to life for New Zealand citizens.
Given that the justifications for this bill have no basis, and also given the
significant constitutional risks, the grounds for this bill are clearly not
consistent with the principles of fundamental justice that's required by Section 8
of NZ BORA.
Thirdly, I just want to highlight specifically the bill's inconsistency with New
Zealand's free trade agreements.
That's particularly so the EU-New Zealand Free Trade Agreement and the
UK-New Zealand Free Trade Agreement.
Both of those free trade agreements contain non-regression clauses.
So, for example, under Article 19.24 of the New
Zealand-EU Free Trade Agreement, a party shall not weaken or
reduce the levels of protection afforded in its environmental or labor law in
order to encourage trade or investment.
So what's extraordinary then is that the government's been quite clear that the
purpose of the bill is to encourage investment, and that clearly engages this
article.
It's important to note that this bill is not an abstract risk to this free trade
agreement. There's mechanisms within the EU through which EU civil
society can and already does raise breaches, and New Zealand's
backtracking has already been raised within the EU domestic advisory group and
within the UK.
This creates significant risk for New Zealand exporters.
So finally, I just want to emphasize that point that this cumulative
inconsistency with so many key international obligations, particularly our free
trade agreements, seriously threatens not only New Zealand's clean, green
reputation, but also our reputation as a stable democracy with a
strong rule of law and access to justice.
That has the potential to create more uncertainty for businesses and international
investors than a court ruling that would've gone through a long, independent,
considered, and evidence-based process.
Thank you.
Thank you, Laura, and thank you, Jennie.
We do have a couple of people with questions, but unfortunately, we have met our
full 10-minute allocation for you, so I'm sorry we won't be able to have them.
But we do appreciate you both submitting to us today and also for your written
submission on the bill as well. So thank you.
Jennie, I'll drop you a note.
Thank you very much. Now, Ms-
Mr. Chair, I wonder if they're still there, this is one of the
major groups involved in this area.
I'd seek leave for just a couple of minutes of questions.
Oh, unfortunately Jennie's just dropped off, Duncan.
I'm still here.
Laura, if you're still here. I'm happy to allow one question either from
Deborah or Steve. But as I do say in my introductory remarks,
five or 10 minutes depending on it, and please do allow time for questions.
So Steve or Deborah, who would like to ask?
Looks like it's you, Steve.
Yeah. Okay. Mine's a pretty quick one.
Your submission's excellent. You acknowledge there's no regime for compensation or
liability currently, and also that there are real
complexities. In extinguishing
this right of people to take tort claims,
is this a big missed opportunity to use the knowledge and the
expertise and the intelligence of the courts to find a way
through
using the development of common law?
Aside from all the moral principles overridden, isn't this a big missed opportunity
for, us to actually use the courts to find
us the way through?
Yes, absolutely, and the point I'd just like to make is that the courts are well
experienced in doing that, so that is the whole purpose of the tort law and the
common law is to find remedies to these types of problems.
Another really important point is that the Supreme Court expressly recognized the
importance of tikanga in the development of this, and this statutory
bar expressly,
forbids that from proceeding. So it halts the court's ability to develop
the common law as it relates to tikanga Maori as well.
So I would agree with you, Steve.
Thank you.
Thanks, Steve. Thank you, Laura and Jennie. Really appreciate your time today.
Members, just before we have Fonterra speak to us on their submission,
would just ask if possible, to keep our cameras on where we can,
just so our submitters know that we're here and present and listening to
what they have to say. Okay. We now have Simon and
Charlotte from Fonterra. Thank you for your written submission.
We have read it. You have 10 minutes.
As I do say to others, please do allow some time at the end of those 10 minutes for
us to ask questions.
Over to you.
Well, kia ora. Good afternoon. Thank you very much.
I'm Simon Tucker, Fonterra's group director of Global
External Affairs. And joining me is our director of sustainability,
Charlotte Rutherford.
And thank you for the opportunity to speak today.
To be clear at the outset, Fonterra supports this legislation.
This is an important issue for our business, for our farmer owners, and we
believe for New Zealand as a whole.
Fonterra and five other companies are facing a lawsuit where the High
Court is being asked to override Parliament's legislative
framework for managing greenhouse gas emissions.
The lawsuit seeks to order us to immediately cut greenhouse
gas emissions to net zero.
In practice, if this were to happen, we would need to
immediately cease operations. This would have
devastating economic, environmental, and social impacts,
as explained in our written comments.
Analysis commissioned by several of the businesses involved, including
Fonterra, found that the impact on New Zealand's GDP from this
lawsuit in the first year could be more than twice the GDP
decline New Zealand experienced during the COVID-19 pandemic in
2020.
Fonterra believes strongly that Parliament should set the framework for how
New Zealand achieves its emissions reduction goals, not the courts.
We do not believe a court case brought by a private individual
which attempts to create a parallel judicial emissions regime
is the right way to address such a fundamental public policy matter.
Our view about the severity of this issue is longstanding, as is
our view that this is an issue for Parliament to resolve.
As you would expect, given the seriousness of this for Fonterra,
for our farmer owners, and for New Zealand,
we have shared these views publicly and with stakeholders from across the
political spectrum over several years.
We do acknowledge that in one case, while working on this issue, a
Fonterra staff member sent a document to a Beehive staff member's personal
email address.
This was inappropriate and contrary to our internal
policies.
This should not distract us from the key issue.
It is Parliament, not the courts, that should set emissions reduction
targets for New Zealand.
Before I close my comments, let me just emphasize that Fonterra's
support for this bill should not be mistaken for a lack of
commitment to climate action.
Fonterra has credible emission reduction targets in place that have
been internationally assessed as being aligned to limiting global
warming to 1.5 degrees.
We are investing hundreds of millions of dollars to continue our significant
decarbonization program.
For example, we are now coal-free in the North Island.
In fact, since 2018, shifting our manufacturing assets off
fossil fuels alone has had the same emission reduction impact
as taking almost 200,000 cars off New Zealand
roads.
We are also working closely with farmer shareholders and other partners
to address on-farm emissions and hit our Scope 3 targets.
This includes Fonterra being the largest private sector investor in AgriZero
NZ, with over $50 million committed.
Fonterra is proud of its world-class approach to emissions reduction
and remains committed to reducing our impact on the environment.
In closing, we would urge the committee to support this legislation
to ensure a nationally coordinated framework for New Zealand's
response to climate change.
Thank you, and happy to answer any questions.
Thanks, Simon. And just before I go to questions, just wanted to see.
Charlotte, do you have any comments you would like to make?
Nothing additional. Happy to move straight to comments. Thank you.
Thank you. We'll start with Dr. Deborah Russell.
Thank you, Chair. Hi, Simon and Charlotte. Nice to see you again.
A couple of things I want to talk about.
One is, Simon, you said in one scenario,
if the court case was upheld, eventually we would have to immediately
stop operations. It's a bit hyperbolistic, isn't it?
Well, that is what is the main central plank of the
plaintiff's case. If he didn't want to stop our operations,
he shouldn't have made that the central plank of his legal case.
Okay. I just feel as though that's, anyway, that's by the by.
Look, the other thing I really wanted to talk about was
our trade agreements and the extent to which
our
actions like this might further create concern around
whether or not we are meeting some of the obligations in our
free trade agreements, particularly with the UK and the EU.
Have you done any analysis of that?
We have done some looking at that, and I understand the government has as well.
To be honest, we're not particularly concerned about that in this situation,
Deborah, because, as I understand, as we understand those
trade agreements, it's about New Zealand fulfilling its obligations,
for example, to the Paris Accord.
And
I think it's pretty clear that Parliament has
passed the Climate Change Reduction Act, which will
seek to achieve that.
I would also note, as I did in my comments, that
we have set emissions reduction targets as a business, which
are also consistent with limiting global warming to 1.5
degrees. So, it's not an issue that we
are concerned about in this instance.
Okay. Thank you.
Thanks, Deborah. We've got a number of people with questions.
We'll go to Steve Abel.
Thank you very much, Mr. Chair. Let me know if I'm cutting out at all.
When did you first lobby the government to
extinguish the right of not only Mike Smith,
but all New Zealanders to take Fonterra to
court for the harms caused by your climate pollution?
I think going back to the initiation of this case, we
were pretty public, Steve, in our comments to
the media, certainly to any politician who would listen
to us, that we thought that this case
was trying to do business that very properly believed
should be under the jurisdiction of Parliament.
We've made no secret of that position, and we've talked to political
stakeholders across
the spectrum over several years on that basis.
I wonder, how do you address
the articulations of deep concern
that that level of direct lobbying to the
Prime Minister's office
expresses an obedience to vested interests
of this government that
raises the accusation of corruption?
And how does that reflect on Fonterra as such
a major company in New Zealand, directly lobbying the Prime Minister's
office with private emails?
I mean, to be honest, we speak to the government, any government,
elected government in New Zealand literally hundreds of times a
year on issues. We are a big business, vertically
integrated across the New Zealand economy.
You want to talk about education and training, you want to talk about trade and
geopolitical risk, you want to talk about energy, transportation,
railways, ports, infrastructure, education.
We have interests in all of those issues, and we firmly believe that
government decision-making is best enabled by having good
position of the facts of both to help them
make good decisions and to understand the impacts of them.
So, this case was seeking to essentially
force New Zealand to stop Fonterra,
to cause us to cease operations. And we thought it was
important that the government understood how seriously that would
impact our farmers, farmers across New Zealand, our regional
communities, and the New Zealand economy.
So we were pretty clear about why we thought it was an important issue.
Thank you so much-
My final one, Mr. Chair, if that's all right, is that-
Sorry, Steve.
Is there currently-- I-
Sorry, Steve, there are a number of other people with questions, so I will need to
go to them in fairness.
Thank you.
We'll go to Carl Bate.
Thanks very much, Chair. Just in terms of the importance of Fonterra to New
Zealand, what amount of
taxation does Fonterra pay? And do you have any
estimate of what your wider dairy or
farmer providers pay into the system?
It's a fair question, Carl. I have to say, I don't know off the top of my head how
much tax is paid. I mean, I would just
observe, among other things, Fonterra is
responsible for very nearly a quarter of New Zealand's total exports,
that foreign exchange coming in. We know, for example, I think it was last year,
we paid out $16 billion to our farmer
owners. We know that they spend much of that into
regional New Zealand, so it does have a very positive impact on the New Zealand
economy.
So if Fonterra was to cease, all of the government's activity
and work across its environmental activity would be put at risk by
that
export earnings not happening and that contribution into the New Zealand taxpayer
also not earning, I would imagine?
Yeah, I think certainly if we were had to cease operations, there'd be
a lot of money, a lot of jobs. I mean, I think the other thing that we would
highlight is if New Zealand stopped producing dairy,
that dairy would be produced in some other part of the world.
So somewhat ironically, that would almost certainly happen with a higher carbon
footprint.
So what's the importance of having a clear pathway and
confidence that that's not a risk Fonterra or its
farmer producer base would face or could face?
Well, I think it comes back to the fact that it's Parliament that really
is the appropriate forum for these massively complicated
national questions to be resolved.
Okay. Well, thank you, Simon, and thank you, Charlotte, for joining us this
afternoon and for your written submission.
Mr. Chair. Mr. Chair, I wonder if we could allow a little leeway
on Fonterra, given they're the main player in this piece of
legislation, to ask a couple more questions.
We have already given them 13, 14 odd minutes, which is over their
10-minute allocation. Unfortunately, we'd be here for the rest of the day,
unfortunately, Steve. I am trying to be as fair as I reasonably can, and hence why
I gave questions to both you and Deborah to begin with.
But I'm doing my best. Doing my best.
But thank you, Simon and Charlotte.
Thank you.
Appreciate your time this afternoon.
We're now going to move to David.
David, great to see you. You're with us. David, we've read your submission.
You have five minutes. Please do leave some time for questions from members.
Tena koutou katoa. Thank you for the opportunity to speak
today. My name is David Laughlin. I'm a registered
architect based in Whangarei, Raglan, and I
appreciate the opportunity to briefly expand on my written submission.
When I first read this bill, I found myself asking a very simple
question: what problem is the bill trying to solve?
The answer I came to was that it seeks to prevent or significantly
reduce climate related tort claims.
That concerns me,
not because I expect a wave of litigation, but because
accountability is one of the foundations of a fair
society.
For a long time, our legal system has recognized a simple principle.
If someone's actions may have caused foreseeable harm,
those affected should have the opportunity to ask a court to
examine the evidence and decide the case on its merits.
This bill would remove that opportunity for an entire category of
claims before the facts can even be considered.
As an architect, I'm required to think well beyond the
present.
The buildings I design may still be standing in 50 or 100 years'
time.
Every decision carries consequences, and accepting
responsibility for those consequences is part of my
profession.
Climate change asks us to think in exactly the same way.
It asks us to consider not only what is convenient today, but
what we leave to those who come after us.
Much of my life has been spent being in or on coastlines,
forests, and rural landscapes across Aotearoa.
Those experiences have reinforced something I believe deeply.
Land and water are never simply economic assets.
They hold ecological relationships, cultural histories, and
communities that have developed over generations
When those relationships are damaged, the effects are rarely confined to
one place or one generation.
For that reason, I don't believe this bill will encourage better environmental
decision-making.
Instead, I'm concerned it sends the message that
reducing legal accountability
is an appropriate response to increasingly complex
environmental challenges.
New Zealand has generally sought to strengthen responsibility where
significant harm may occur.
In my view, this bill moves in the opposite direction.
For those reasons, I respectfully ask the committee to recommend the
bill not proceed.
""Thank you.
Thank you, David. I will just look to see if any members have a question here.
Not at this time, and that's no reflection of your written or oral submission,
David, and we do thank you for joining us this afternoon, so thank you very much.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you, David.
We now come to Z Energy, and we will just get them to come
up online.
Fantastic. Hi, Patricia. We can see you. That's great.
We've got you down for 10 minutes. We have read your written submission,
but please do allow some time for members to ask questions.
I'm sure there will be some, but we're over to you both.
Tēnā koe koutou.
Thank you for the opportunity to submit. My name is Lindis Jones.
I'm the Chief Executive of Z Energy.
With me is Patricia Green, Z's General Counsel, who will
take the committee through our submission in more detail.
We support this bill for three reasons.
First, climate policy should be set by Parliament, not the courts.
Climate change presents some of the most difficult choices our country faces.
How we reduce emissions affects jobs, household costs,
energy security, investment, and economic
resilience. Those are questions of public
policy that should be balanced by elected representatives on behalf of all
New Zealanders.
Second reason is that while climate litigation can have a certain appeal,
it is ultimately a poor substitute for climate policy.
Faced with a challenge as significant as climate change, it's understandable to
want a simple answer or a single party to hold accountable.
But New Zealand's energy transition will not be delivered company by company
or court case by court case.
It requires a coherent framework that balances competing interests,
weighs difficult trade-offs, and applies consistently across the economy.
We already have that framework in the hard-fought-for Climate Change Response Act
and the Emissions Trading Scheme.
Third,
certainty matters. New Zealand needs significant long-term investment to
support both energy security and the transition to lower
emissions forms of energy.
Clear, stable, and durable policy settings give
businesses the confidence to make these investments over very long
time horizons.
The reason we support this bill is not simply because Z is a defendant in the Smith
versus Fonterra litigation.
The issue at stake is much larger than that.
Clear, stable, and durable-- oh, sorry.
It's--
no? Just...
Cool.
I'll start again. The reason we support this bill is not simply because Z is a
defendant in the Smith v. Fonterra litigation.
The issue at stake is much larger than that.
Also, we're not here to comment on any individual or details of that specific
litigation.
Even if we weren't involved in those proceedings, we would still support the bill
because we believe climate policy works best when it is applied
consistently across the economy
rather than individually through court cases focused on a small number
of individual companies.
But also, let me be clear, our support for this bill should not be mistaken for a
lack of commitment to climate action.
We support New Zealand's transition to a lower emissions future and are investing
in that transition today.
Supporting this bill is about how climate policy is made,
not whether emissions should be reduced.
The fundamental question before the committee is not whether climate change
requires action.
It does. The question is, who should determine New Zealand's pathway forward?
And we fundamentally believe that responsibility sits properly
with a democratically elected parliament. Thank you for your time.
I'll hand to Patricia.
Thank you.
From a legal perspective, the claims before the courts remain novel and
unresolved.
The litigation seeks to establish forms of climate-related liability that have
not previously been recognized by New Zealand courts.
More recently, the remedies sought have expanded to include immediate
net zero obligations for the defendants.
We have presented the committee with evidence about the potential consequences of
those remedies. Independent modeling indicates that the
remedies sought against the defendants could reduce New Zealand's
GDP by at least $21.9 billion
over five years.
If similar obligations were extended across other businesses and
sectors, the impact could be substantially larger again.
This highlights the nature of the claims before the court.
They are not directed at a single activity or a discrete harm.
They seek outcomes with potentially economy-wide
implications
There is also an important issue of certainty.
Businesses make long-term decisions about investment, infrastructure, and
employment.
A stable and predictable legal framework helps provide the
confidence needed to make those decisions.
Where lawful activities may become subject to new and uncertain forms of
liability, that uncertainty can affect long-term planning
and investment.
That is why we consider it important that the bill applies to current
proceedings as well as future claims.
Without that clarification, uncertainty could continue for many
years while the litigation proceeds through the courts.
The bill provides certainty about the role of tort law in addressing climate
change by preserving the existing role of the courts in enforcing
the statutory mechanisms through which climate-related issues can
continue to be considered.
We're now happy to take any questions.
Thank you, Lyndis, and thank you, Patricia, for your submission.
In balance of fairness, we'll start our questioning with Steve Abel.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. It's very kind.
There is currently no law that requires you to reduce
your climate pollution or remedy anyone for the
harms caused by your climate pollution.
Is that your understanding?
So, in terms of cl-
Sorry, just having sound issues there,
Steve.
Well, the first thing I'd say is the products that we sell and the
emissions they create, we don't deny.
However, how we go about reducing those emissions
in amongst all the other emissions that
are produced in the New Zealand economy is a complex set of choices, and there are
already rules and legislation set out in the Climate Change Response Act.
Just unilaterally choosing one company or one sector
runs the risk of adverse impacts across
society and the economy.
Do you not think that lobbying directly to extinguish
the democratic right of all New Zealand citizens to
hold you accountable for the harms caused by your
pollution
has the very nasty taint of
problematic influence of vested interests on our
democracy, and that's exactly why the public is so disturbed
by this law?
I think, Steven, this is not about whether emissions
should reduce.
This is not about whether we as a country should deal with the challenges of
climate change. We absolutely should and have.
It's how we go about doing that. These challenges in front of
us as a country are complex and require trade-offs,
and those trade-offs are best made by elected officials,
not by individual judges or courts that
don't have all that information or responsibility available to them.
That's our-
Because those elected officials can more readily be influenced by big, powerful
companies like your own. Is that what you're saying?
I reject that framing.
All right. Dr. Deborah Russell.
Actually, I've heard a few questions, so I'll just stand down in favor of Camilla.
Otherwise, we may not get to her.
Okay. Camilla Belich.
Thank you. I just wanted to ask, why did you specifically
lobby the government to introduce a law that would
not allow Mr. Smith's existing proceedings
to proceed
rather than lobbying the government to
wait until after the High Court determined Mr. Smith's case?
Oh.
So, the case in front of the
courts at the moment started in 2019.
It's set down to, in front of the court in
2027, and undoubtedly there's likely to be a series
of appeals after that. That'll take us well into the next decade.
That's a long time for significant uncertainty in terms of
how we can progress the investments needed to help our customers
transition, and that level of uncertainty we think is untenable, where the
government has the opportunity in front of them now to make a
choice to reinforce the Climate Change Response Act in the
coordinated, efficient way that that gives us the best chance
as a country to deal with the challenges in front of us in terms of reducing
emissions.
Quick supplementary, Mr. Chair.
Yeah.
Just in terms of that answer,
wouldn't it have been better to actually see if what you were
trying to prevent was actually ordered by the courts rather than
preemptively asking the government to extinguish those rights?
Because it might be that the uncertainty that you're worried
about never actually eventuated and, as you say,
it was unlikely to happen until
many years into the future.
It's many years into the future, and that's a lot of uncertainty
and
challenge for several large companies across New
Zealand that would just like to get on and deliver for our customers now,
while helping our customers transition to a lower carbon future.
It's not only uncertainty, but the significant
expense that goes with that. And we've already got-- This isn't a
discussion about whether we should transition or lower emissions or not.
We are. It's actually what's the most efficient, effective way to do that on
behalf of all New Zealanders, and I just can't believe under any circumstance
that that sits with the courts to make that call on behalf of us
all.
Okay. Time for one final question from Carl Bates.
Thanks, Chair. Just in regards to the challenges that have been raised around
the lobbying activity that's taken place, would it surprise you to hear
that as parliamentarians, we are lobbied by a whole range of
organizations, individuals, businesses, on a daily
basis, and it wouldn't be a surprise that some of those
discussions lead to parliamentary legislation being
introduced to the House?
Yeah, I accept that assertion, Carl, but I also
want to point to
that the discussion around the lobbying and the
presentation of evidence and information to the government has got away from the
substance of this discussion, and that's unfortunate.
Exactly. Agree with you.
Thank you very much, Lindis and Patricia.
We really appreciate your time this afternoon and for joining us, so thank you.
Okay, members, we now move to Port Stafford Limited and
JAFL, and we've got Tony and Bridget joining
us this afternoon. Both are online already.
So as you'll know, we've read your submissions. Great to see you both.
Please leave a little bit of time at the end for any questions that members may
have. Over to you.
Thanks, Tom. As you have explained, we are appearing on
behalf of Port Stafford Limited and JAFL, who represent over
3,600 investors who sought relief in the Horton and
Saunders cases, more commonly known as the Feltex litigation.
I am the managing director of Franks Ogilvie, a commercial public law firm here in
Wellington, and appearing with me is Tony Gavagan, who is the director
of Port Stafford and JAFL.
This submission supports this bill.
Smith & Fontara was a strikeout decision.
Ultimately, the Supreme Court did not finally determine whether there would be
climate tort liability.
It held that there were claims that should be allowed to proceed to trial in
circumstances where Parliament had not clearly displaced tort liability in the
climate field.
This bill
basically supplies the clarity that the court said was missing.
It confirms that emission-related climate change effects are to be dealt with
through the Climate Change Response Act and public regulation, not
private tort litigation. It is not Parliament defying the
courts. It is Parliament doing only what Parliament can do, which
is setting a general rule for a systemic problem.
If it was to be applied only prospectively, as some have claimed it
could, it would not address that live uncertainty that Smith &
Fontara has created.
We also note that the drafting is broad because the public choice and the
policy choice here is broad. Tort law is not to be the
mechanism, as this bill sets out, for allocating responsibility for
emissions-only related climate change effects.
Now, you may be asking what is the relevance of the Feltex litigation and why are
we presenting today? The Feltex litigation is a practical
comparator to these circumstances.
Briefly, for those members not familiar with Feltex, this was a major
investor representative action arising from the 2004
public offer of shares in Feltex carpets.
Thousands of shareholders alleged that the prospectus was misleading,
and when the shares, sorry, were issued at $1.70,
Feltex later failed, and investors suffered substantial losses.
The case was, in brief, managed in two stages.
At the first stage, shareholders attained a partial success,
basically at the Supreme Court, finding that one allegation of misrepresentation
was established concerning a 2004 revenue forecast in that
prospectus.
Stage two would have dealt with reliance, causation, loss, and remedy,
but it never happened.
What this case shows is that there was a procedural and
systemic legal problem that was left to judge-made law without an adequate
statutory framework. I'm going to turn to Tony now to provide you
with his personal experience of how that affected him and
other investors.
You're just on mute, Tony.
We can't hear you. I'm sorry.
In the interest of time, it might be best if I provide, these
are Tony's words, not my own.
Great.
But just providing, and if Tony is able to resolve his tech
issues, he can jump in.
So Tony was involved in the Feltex litigation for many years, as
expected, and for him, it taught him what judge-made law means in
practice when thousands of people are caught in a systemic claim without a clear
statutory authority.
It involved thousands of investors.
The prospectus, in his opinion, was misleading, and this was
established in one part, as we said, by the Supreme Court, and it was meant to
go to stage two, including issues of remedy.
So noting importantly that this was a right was established and it
didn't actually ever receive a remedy.
Stage two never happened. The investors got the
significant finding, but this caused a significant access to
justice failure, and it became part of the process of forging New
Zealand's judge-made class action regime that we see today.
In this case, private litigants should not have had to carry the cost of
building the legal machinery that Parliament should have supplied, and to
find that failure is those thousands of investors
This is not an abstract about civil procedure, although that we could go into the
depths of that. It was about a Supreme Court finding that had no practical
path to remedy, and this is how it connects to this bill.
Tony has applied that this is why the bill matters to him.
It shows that Parliament is prepared to say that this field should not be
left to judge-made law, and he supports that in the climate
context. He also asks the committee to note, and you'll see that
in the written submission, that Feltex raises the same broader
institutional problem in representative actions, litigation funding, and fair
trading remedies. In the exceptional case where investors
suffered total or near total loss after investing, based on an
untrue registered prospectus, Parliament should consider whether a
buyback or wholemade remedy should be available.
Tony absolutely accepts that this is separate from the subject of the climate bill
that is currently before you but shows that the principle should apply.
When judge-made law has produced systemic uncertainty or
injustice, Parliament should and can legislate.
I'm not sure, Tony, whether you've managed to get sound.
I think I have. Can you hear that, Bridget?
We can.
Yes.
Thank you very much. I've got little to add other than to say
that in the Feltex case, there was actual harm.
We've been in the process since 2008.
That's an extraordinarily long period of time,
and we have not achieved justice.
Thanks, Tony. Thank you, Bridget. We do have time for questions.
First person with their hand raised was Carl Bates.
You're just on mute, Carl.
Ah, okay.
Oh, that was the hand not down from last time. Apologies.
All right. Camilla Belich.
Thank you. Thanks for your submission, both of you.
In your submission, you state that the Parliament should
not
shy away from corrective action when
there has been a decision by the courts.
And I just wondered,
in this case it appears to me that the courts have not been able
to make a determination. And so isn't it a bit premature
to suggest that Parliament
is making corrective action when the case is yet to be determined?
Or maybe you have a view on the timing of the case that you
would like to share.
I think Bridget should address that. That's more of a legal question.
I think there has been a determination that it is open to the courts
to find a climate change tort liability.
And I think the point made earlier by other submitters
is that the wheels of justice are incredibly slow, and in that
time you create significant uncertainty and significant
cost. Therefore, it is appropriate for Parliament to
determine at this stage that they wish to intervene and correct
the decision so far of the court.
Camilla, do you have a supplementary or you're
okay?
No,
Mr. Chair.
Question from Steve Abel.
Thank you very much, Mr. Chair.
Look, in terms of the
slowness of the wheels of
the courts,
isn't that the exact problem we're facing with climate change, the
painfully slow lack of action from the state which has caused
someone to take a civil claim? And here we have billions of
people caught in an existential threat.
Shouldn't we be using the full faculties of our society's machinery in
terms of the estates of the courts and the Parliament to find
ways through and allow such an important court case to
seek out whether there is a right of remedy
for a private citizen
to play out? Isn't that exactly why we should let this run its course?
And if the court oversteps, the Parliament can step in and
amend that.
If I could-
So-- Oh, sorry, Tony. You go ahead.
If I could respond to that.
This bill will pass with urgency and the certainty
will exist.
That just does not happen in the legal system
where, as Davey Salmon said to me a few years ago,
if you can get one major aspect of a major
case through the Supreme Court per annum,
you're doing really well.
But the certainty exists for who? Not for those suffering the
existential harms of climate change.
Well, Parliament's elected by the people of New Zealand, so
we elect the people who will represent our
views. And I think the views that we've heard so far from the
people who also support this bill
cover tens of thousands of New Zealanders.
And billions of dollars of capital commercial interest.
Yes, for sure. And that's what keeps us alive.
And
we can prove in the Feltex case, by analogy, there has been
actual harm.
At a risk of being seen to be a heretic, there's many,
many issues about the connection between the
parties that are being looked at and the alleged harm.
Thank you, Tony, and thank you, Bridget.
Appreciate both of you joining us this afternoon for your written and your oral
submission. Thank you very much.
Thank you, members. We now come to Oliver.
Hi, Oliver. Thank you for joining us.
We have received and read your written submission, so thank you very much.
You have five minutes. Please do allow some time for questions as well.
Over to you
Thank you. Can you hear me okay?
We can.
Excellent. Well, my name is Oliver Hails.
I'm an international law lecturer currently based at the London School of
Economics. So thanks for the opportunity to present.
I will leave
a
few moments for questions at the end.
So I'm presenting my view in opposition to this bill.
We all know that Mike Smith won his appeal, and now you're being
asked to stop the case going to trial.
Let me begin by pointing out that this type of bill would breach one
of the oldest rules of international law
if it were to affect a foreign national doing business in New
Zealand.
For example, many years ago, an American gold miner doing
business in South Africa won his case before the South
African High Court.
Then Parliament passed a law which declared his
mining licenses invalid and prevented him from claiming
any remedy before the courts.
Subsequently, an international tribunal held that this act of
Parliament, quote,
"Did violence to fundamental principles of justice recognized
in every enlightened community."
And we call this a denial of justice.
Now, of course, Mr. Smith is a New Zealand citizen,
but I want you to hold in mind this key point that you're being invited to
treat him worse than the international minimum
standard that is expected by overseas
investors.
In fact, the bill is inconsistent with New Zealand's international
obligations in at least three key areas.
So first, the bill is inconsistent with
the climate obligations confirmed by the International Court of
Justice and welcomed by New Zealand recently in the
UN General Assembly.
A bill to bar tort liability of this type seems to
fall short of the duty to use all available means to
regulate high-emitting companies, which would include maintaining access to
justice.
Second, the bill is inconsistent with human rights obligations, and
indeed, the UN Human Rights Committee, in a case involving New Zealand, has
confirmed that a country legislating to
prevent a pending case would breach the rights to a
fair and public hearing.
And that's exactly what this bill does, which would expose New Zealand
to possible censure from a universal human rights monitoring body
if indeed an individual communication were to be brought before that forum,
which might be something to think about for this Justice Committee.
Third, the bill is inconsistent with some of New Zealand's trade
agreements, which prevent the weakening of environmental law for the
purpose of encouraging investment.
The minister has said that's the very point of this bill.
So in other words, the bill exposes New Zealand to complaints from,
say, the EU and other trading partners because it
distorts the level playing field between these trading
partners.
So to conclude, the bill is meant to give businesses
certainty and to reduce their legal risk.
Instead, in my view, it increases New Zealand's own legal risk, including
through possible international proceedings and its reputational
risk in diplomatic and economic relations.
More generally, this denial of access to justice through legislative
interference signals, I think, a sovereign risk of regulatory
turbulence when future governments are obliged to change tack,
which of course would undermine the very investor confidence
that this bill is meant to protect.
So thanks for your attention. I look forward to any questions you might have.
Thank you, Oliver. We have a question from Dr. Deborah Russell.
Thank you, Oliver. It's a really interesting submission. I just want to clarify.
You're at the LSE, so why are you commenting on this law in
particular? What's your interest in it, aside from the obvious international law
implications, but...
Well, of course, I am a New Zealand national.
I've been out of the country for about eight years, though I am returning soon.
And I have an academic interest in international law,
focused on energy investment, environmental
disputes, and I thought there was an international dimension to this issue that
might otherwise go underexplored.
Yeah. Thank you for giving us your expertise on it. Appreciate it.
And a question from Rima Naqvi.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Hi, Oliver. Kia ora.
Kia ora.
Thanks for your submission. I just want to ask, so would you
say that emissions-related climate harm is a really
important and profound subject matter?
Emissions-related climate harm, certainly it is an important and
profound subject matter, yes.
And such a profound and important matter,
decisions about it should be made by a court, not by
Parliament, since it's so profound and important?
Well, I think the
character of harm to the climate system from greenhouse gas
emissions has called for this duty of due diligence in all
states to use all means at their disposal
to regulate the conduct, in particular of private emitters.
So the-
Or missing .
Yeah.
Thank you, Oliver. Really appreciate you joining us.
I'm sure it's the early hours of the morning,
where you are, but thank you very much for your written and your oral submission as
well.
Thank you.
Okay, members, we now have Business New Zealand, and we're going to have Katherine
and Ben joining us. Katherine's online already, which is great.
Katherine, you've got 10 minutes. We've read your written submission.
Please do leave some time at the end for questions that members may have.
Over to you.
Thank you very much. And it's just me, Katherine Beard, Director of Advocacy for
Business New Zealand
Thank you for the opportunity. Business New Zealand supports this Amendment
Bill.
This kind of litigation needs to be ruled out once and for all by
Parliament. Failure to do so leaves every business in New
Zealand at risk of being sued for greenhouse gas emissions,
particularly the energy intensive trade exposed firms that need to be
globally competitive to stay in business.
Climate change is a global problem and needs a global and a country level
response, which is how it is being addressed internationally.
If New Zealand shut down completely and ceased all commercial and
industrial activity, it would have little impact on global
emissions, since we comprise 0.17% of
emissions.
We already have a legislative and cross-party response to
emissions reductions in the Climate Change Response Act
2002, that has us on an emissions reduction
path to 2050.
We have an emissions trading scheme that puts a price on all emissions and
fuel. This is a least cost approach to emission reductions,
which is not only important to keep our businesses viable, but to keep the
cost of living reasonable as well.
I would suggest that any political party that tried to take a high cost
approach to emission reductions would not last long in government.
If the New Zealand Parliament allowed a system whereby businesses that are already
paying for emissions were also able to be sued through the courts,
we would become a very damaged economy very quickly,
and I can supply the select committee with two different economic reports to
back this up.
No other country in the world would let their businesses be sued in the courts
for greenhouse gas emissions when they already had a legislated
approach. It would be economic lunacy, frankly,
and they would move quickly to fix it.
The select committee should also take into account carbon leakage, which is
what happens when the cost of emission reductions in one country is
significantly higher than other competing countries.
Businesses can simply shift production to other countries with the lower
cost approach to emission reductions.
Often this is worse for greenhouse gas emissions, as the production of
goods may be more carbon intensive, and we have not only lost jobs
and goods being made domestically, but the climate is worse off as
well.
If we don't stop this kind of litigation, New Zealand will be very unattractive
to foreign investment as well. If Z Energy was shut down, for
example, there would be one less competitor in that market, and
no international business would be keen to take their place.
Thank you.
Thank you, Catherine.
Fantastic. You left plenty of time for questions, and we've got a question from
Todd Stevenson.
Oh, thank you, Catherine. A couple of things you mentioned.
You mentioned having this parallel, basically the Climate Reduction Act and then
particularly,
potentially sued in the courts as well, would lead to a damaged economy, I think
was your words. Can you outline what
that would look like practically?
Oh, look, it would be very significant, particularly when one
of the companies in the gun for this is one of our biggest exporters
and employers in New Zealand.
We've actually done a bit of analysis on what would happen
just if we priced agricultural emissions as an example,
and regional New Zealand is actually really hard hit.
So, you're talking,
just looking at the numbers, 54,000 jobs in
key upstream and downstream industries nationally are
vulnerable.
And
on farm employment in sheep, beef, and dairy
employ a further 44,000 people. So, you're talking
100,000 jobs just if you put a price on agricultural
emissions, and a lot of the impact of that is
actually closure of the meat
processing and the dairy processing companies.
So a lot of these energy intensive businesses are regionally based,
and they're also big employers.
And just one quick follow-up, if I might, Mr. Chair.
You also mentioned obviously, and we've actually heard evidence this morning, that
if this court case went on, it could take many, many
years to resolve and that can create some
uncertainty. In your experience, Catherine,
how do companies make investment decisions and what kind of timelines are they
looking at and what kind of certainty do they need?
Well, look, I think one of the downsides of this kind of litigation
dragging on for years is
it's a distraction to the businesses, but it's a huge
cost. Millions and millions of dollars are spent on lawyers'
fees and court time and all of that kind of thing.
We think we've got a productivity problem in New Zealand.
We need to be spending all that money on innovation and R&D
and growing our businesses. We already
have a system to reduce greenhouse gas emissions.
This would be doubling up, and would be very detrimental.
Thank you.
And a question from Carl Bates.
Thanks very much, Chair. Thank you, Catherine.
In your experience, who ultimately pays
these costs that these companies are incurring
from having to defend these actions, and what impact
does it have on the New Zealand consumer if a business
such as Z Energy was to fail, in terms of where they would get
that product from?
Well, look, everything ultimately flows through to consumers, and that
is actually why
dealing with climate change globally is such a wicked problem,
because politicians tend to like to promise the
public and voters that this will be painless and low cost
and a better future. And yes, we will get to a better future, but it's
actually a wicked problem because it's expensive to get there in
the short term. So, that's why it really matters that we take
a
really thoughtful, gradual
reduction to 2050 that businesses can afford, because they
pass those costs on to consumers.
And if you lose one of your energy suppliers,
you've just reduced competition.
So there's less competition and your fuel prices are probably going to go
up.
Thank you. And a final question from Dr. Deborah Russell.
Thank you, Catherine. You talked about uncertainty for business.
What kind of uncertainty is climate change creating for business?
Look, climate change is
a thing that businesses have to deal with, but we have to remember it's a
global phenomena. Nothing we do in New Zealand is going to stop
the march of the temperatures and what's
happening on our coastal areas.
It's a global problem. We've all got to work together on it.
But actually,
no country on its own is going to solve the problem, and particularly not a small
one
down where we're based geographically. So we have to do our part.
I think that's the reason we've got so much of our
stuff around climate written into our trade agreement.
So if we don't meet our climate commitments, how's that going to
work in terms of uncertainty for business around our trade agreements?
Look, I'm really confident that New Zealand's doing a good job
vis-à-vis other countries.
I spent six years working on climate change policy back in the
2000s, and
I've looked at a lot of the other approaches to emission reductions
being taken internationally.
I think New Zealand has one of the most comprehensive emission trading schemes in
the world. The European Union, for example, excludes a lot of
the energy intensive industries from their scheme.
So, I think New Zealand's absolutely pulling its weight and doing
as much as any other country, and I'm confident too, that our businesses
have been on a, I said I've been doing this issue since the
2000s. They've all reduced emissions
enormously. And I do have a report that shows how they
stack up against their international competitors, and it's good.
So-
It's not so much the international competitors, it's the commitments that are
written into our trade agreements with such as the UK and the
EU, where we can't go backwards in terms of any
climate work.
But we're not going backwards because we already have a legislative
approach to 2050, which is what all the other countries are doing as
well. What you're doing in introducing court cases, which are
random, is you're basically doubling up on the
commitment.
I disagree.
Thank you very much, Catherine. Really appreciate both your written and oral
submission today. So thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you, members. We're now going to come to Cody.
And I think Cody is online with us already.
There he is.
Great to have you with us. We have read your written submission.
We have you for five minutes, and if you can just leave a little bit of time at the
end for some questions. But over to you.
Tena koutou katoa. I worked at the Marsden Point
refinery from around 2007, have lived
nearby in rural Kaka in One Tree Point, and am a father of four.
I witnessed emergency shutdowns, major flaring, and leaks.
I saw how quickly operations could become dangerous.
I understand local pollution and climate change are different
legal issues. I am not claiming these incidents
prove Mike Smith's case. These taught me that the
regulations do not remove every risk or
answer every question of responsibility.
Families and communities still need independent legal
accountability. The defendant
companies argue before the Supreme Court that this
legislation exceeds the court's
competence and should be left to Parliament.
The Supreme Court unanimously reinstated the
claims. It did not decide Mike Smith would
win.
Applying the strikeout test, it decided the claims were
not bound to fail, and that
tikanga responsibility
amendments require evidence
at trial.
That matters because tort law is common law.
Judges have always developed it case by
case through evidence,
procedure,
and legal principle. That does not mean
judges set national climate policy.
Parliament sets targets and regulatory schemes.
Court decides whether one person was legally wrong,
and whether the law
provides a remedy.
The common law has repeatedly adapted to new
technologies and harms. Climate change raises
difficult questions of cumulative harm
that calls for judicial examination,
not prohibition. Parliament
had not excluded that role. The Climate
Change Response Act created regulation
while Section 23 of the Resource Management Act
reserved independent common laws
and rights. This bill closes that pathway
before the court that perform its
function. I accept that Parliament is sovereign, but legal
power does not answer what- Whether this use
of
that power is justified. The bill reaches past
conduct, identifies Mike
V Fonterra by name and court number, terminates
unfinished proceedings, removes damages,
declares the injunctions,
covers existing and future torts, and denies
compensation. Under Section 5 of the
New Zealand Bill of Rights Act, limits on rights must be
demonstrably justified and no
broader than responsibly necessary.
Regulatory standards principles also required
scrutiny of retrospective
consultation alternatives
and
preparationally
...
The weakness is minimal impairment.
The Parliament
could let the trial finish, legislation
prospectively
preserve control non-monetary
remedies,
provide a replacement remedy, or require
independent review.
When ACC displaced personal injury torts,
Parliament supplied replacement compensation.
This bill removes every meaningful tort remedy and
replaces it with nothing. The government says the bill
creates business certainty, but officials found
no measurable impact on business confidence,
identified no public material suggested the decision
was discouraging investment and
did not consult the parties. High emitting
sectors, the wide business community or Maori.
The bill may instead create disputes
over related activities' indirect effects,
overseas conduct, and the boundary between local
pollution and climate harm. Officials were
advised that statutory bars may reduce
clarity and that
litigation
would likely continue as people test the bar's scope.
Business depend on stable law and
confidence that existing disputes
will be determined by courts rather than changed
through case-specific interventions.
Section 274
applies regardless of
whether another law applied,
whether it was obeyed, or whether
enforcement occurred. It does
not
legalize a breach, but it
gives the same climate tort immunity
to complaint and
non-complaint businesses. If regulation
is the complete alternative, why does
immunity remain when that regulation was breached?
There is also a serious transparency
issue. A six-page proposal concerning Smith
v Fonterra sought regulation
preventing climate tort claims and expressively included
Mr. Smith's proceedings. It relied on
sovereign risk investment funding and insurance
claims but identified no modeling, canceled
investments, withdrawn lender or
insurer that had changed position.
The bill adapts the same central mechanism
and
rationale then goes further. It expressly
protects an overseas person using the Overseas
Investment Act definition. It also protects the Crown
Ministry and government departments.
I am not
alleging criminal corruption or claiming I
can prove who drafted the bill. The document created
a legitimate appearance of targeting
lawmaking requiring
independent scrutiny. Who
requested those protections and what
independently verified evidence supported
them? Tikanga is
directly affected. The bill places Tikanga
Maori conceptions
of non-physical and non-economical harm inside
the prohibition. He Hunga
Rioira Maori said Tikanga requires an evidential
inquiry and that Tikanga evidence would be critical at
trial. The bill prevents that inquiry.
It may be argued that
causation is difficult.
New Zealand's global share is small.
The ETS regulates emissions or
litigation could affect jobs. Those
matters are for trial. Mike Smith must still
prove standing, harm, duty, causation,
and an appropriate remedy. Courts can refuse,
narrow, or suspend an injunction, grant only a
declaration, award costs, or control proceedings.
Allowing this trial does not make every emitter liable.
It allows the common law safeguards to operate.
My request is simple. Allow the trial to proceed.
If Mike Smith cannot prove the case, the court can dismiss it.
If the trial reveals a genuine conflict with Parliament framework,
Parliament can legislate afterwards
prospectively and
On of actual findings, I am
not asking judges to set New Zealand climate
policy. I am asking that they be allowed to perform
their constitutional role, hearing evidence, determining legal
responsibility, and developing the common law carefully
on one case at a time. I am not asking
Parliament to decide that Mike Smith is right.
I am asking Parliament not to declare him wrong before
his evidence has been heard. As a-
Thank you, Cody
... forestry worker-
... nearby resident, and father of four, I do not believe families,
communities, responsibilities, businesses should not lose equal access
to law because the harm is difficult or the defendant powerful.
If this case is weak, let it fail on the evidence.
Do not extinguish it before the evidence is heard.
That is not regulatory certainty.
It is respective immunity. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Cody, for your submission and for joining us this afternoon.
We have gone significantly over time, so we thank you for joining us.
Thank you.
We now come to Sam Bookman, who is going to speak to us for five minutes.
Thank you, Sam, for your patience. You have five minutes.
Please allow some time for questions at the end. Over to you.
Hi, kia ora koutou. I'm Sam Bookman.
I'm a lecturer at the University of Melbourne, where I study and teach both tort
law and climate change. And I just want to make three key points.
So the first is around the issue of parallel regimes.
I just want to stress that, in my experience and expertise, it's very
normal for public and private law regimes to operate in
tandem. I think this concern about a parallel regime of regulation is somewhat
overblown. One of the reasons for that is in order to precisely to
protect individual rights, and balance those against the public
interest and incorporate them together.
So the RMA, which has been in place for decades, expressly preserves tort law for
that very reason. Public law sets overall obligations to
society. Private law governs those relationships between parties.
So for instance, a factory that complies with resource permits may still be liable
if it pollutes a neighbor's water.
Likewise, the ETS regulates New Zealand's headline emissions and everyone's
responsibility in reaching them, not what happens when someone is
harmed. So in environmental matters, these regimes work best when they
operate together. Secondly, the role of Parliament.
So, these regimes do collide sometimes. Courts are not perfect.
Micro-level decisions don't always produce ideal macro-level outcomes.
And then deciding what to do then is, of course, Parliament's role.
But at present, we're not seeing any collision between those two regimes.
We don't actually know what tort liability for climate harm would even look like,
and there's no regulation under New Zealand's existing public law for climate
harm or remedies at all. The only economic modeling we've seen is that of
Fonterra's, and that's based on the most extreme assumptions about the litigation's
outcome, which I'll talk about more in a moment.
Where genuine collisions do need adjustment or overhaul, as New Zealand has
seen with ACC, resolving those is a complex policy
task that takes years, takes extensive consultation and evidence.
This bill is not about Parliament answering those questions.
It's about shutting down the only active decision-making process that we have
ongoing on these processes, and deciding that private emitters don't pay
a share of responding to climate harms, and doing so in an
incredibly rushed process.
Finally, I want to say a little bit more about what the Smith and Fonterra
litigation actually seeks and what its potential impacts are on New Zealand,
because I think there's been some pretty wild speculation about that in some of the
previous submissions. So Mr. Smith's case seeks a range of
different remedies. One of those is a form of immediate injunction.
In my view, it's pretty unlikely that a court would award that remedy.
Of course, Parliament can respond to that kind of remedy if it were to
eventuate. I think it's far more likely to adopt other remedies that don't have
that kind of doomsday effect claimed by Fonterra.
I'd just be very clear that no one's suggesting Fonterra cease all operations
tomorrow, such as obligations to reach net zero by
2020 or start reducing emissions.
Nor are Fonterra or others uniquely disadvantaged internationally.
Their
competitors overseas face very similar cases and obligations.
The suggestion by Business New Zealand that it's lunacy to allow these cases to
proceed is just not borne out. In the United States and
Europe and the United Kingdom, these kinds of cases go hand in
hand all the time, and it's the same kind of accountability sought by
litigants in those countries as well.
So I'll leave it there, and happy to take questions.
Thank you, Sam. We have a question from Dr. Deborah Russell.
Thank you, Sam. I see that you're a New Zealander, and so appreciate you
having your input onto this. I just want to go to those two things
you touched on just most recently.
You said that what Fonterra said earlier, that they'd have to stop
operations immediately, is actually hyperbole.
You think that's, is that an okay assessment of it?
I think that's right. I mean, look, it is one of the remedies
sought in the litigation, is an immediate injunction.
I think it is extremely unlikely that a court would award that.
The signals that we saw from the Supreme Court was definitely much more of a focus
on declaratory rather than injunctive remedies.
I think, the focus of remedies that we see in public nuisance
cases is much broader and more creative than that, and I think it's far
more likely that any one of the other five or six remedies that they have sought
in the alternative are more likely.
In the event that a court did issue a remedy that had the
inevitable consequence of Fonterra ceasing operations,
then we can see how fast Parliament can move
to address those issues. I just think that's enormously speculative at
this stage to suggest that's what's going on.
Thank you. And I see you teach in tort law and climate change.
Do you know of other cases around the world where tort law has been used
successfully in a climate Case or that are
underway?
So there's a range of cases underway, particularly in North America and
in Europe. In Europe, some of those cases have been found,
liability has been established at a trial level, though not
upheld. And usually what happens precisely in those cases is
courts come to a conclusion that the kind of injunctive relief, extreme
injunctive relief, is not appropriate, and what's needed is some kind of more
declaratory creative approach. Those cases remain ongoing, and I think they provide
a very fruitful dialogue for the establishment of policy in this
area.
Thank you.
Thank you, Sam. We have met our allocation of time. I'm sorry, Carl.
But we appreciate you joining us this afternoon, and for your written submission,
too.
Thank you.
Okay, members, next submitter is Lingyi Wang,
and he is with us now. Lingyi, thank you for joining us.
You have five minutes. We have read your submission, and if you can just leave some
time at the end for questions.
Thank you.
Tena koutou katoa. Ko Ling toku ingoa.
So I agree with the submission made by Lawyers for Climate
Action. I just want to make three points.
First is a fresh point, and then I want to clarify two points I made in the written
submission. So first, I see that the bill is analogous to the
statutory bar in tort to seek compensation in personal injury
under Accident Compensation Act.
However, that bar is accompanied by ACC itself.
The idea is that instead of a court deciding which person
causing personal injury paying who, ACC, that
means the government, will pay instead, and the government pays for the cost
through ACC levy, so no one is out of pocket unfairly.
Going back to this bill, given that every household suffers
material injury because of climate change, for example,
direct out-of-pocket expenses due to climate
change-related flood or through increase in
house insurance premium, what the bill does is
statutory bar anyone seeking compensation in tort from
those who cause climate change. There's no ACC
equivalent in this bill to compensate household for their
out-of-pocket expenses. So this government even
explicitly exempt agriculture sector from the emission trading
scheme, so there's even less avenue to pay for climate
change-induced damages. Therefore, I do not see the fairness
in this bill.
So this is the first point. The second point I want to reiterate is that
the bill takes away the autonomy of the court.
The Smith and
Fonterra decision is not saying that the respondents definitely have to
pay. The court is simply saying that there's a case for them to
answer, and it is still an open question who has to pay
and for how much. This bill, however, bars the court from
even investigating an open question.
So in this sense, I would say that this government is behaving like a nanny state.
The third is that I do not see a
democratic mandate given to National,
New Zealand First or ACT to enact this bill.
So I do not see from the policy platform in
2023 or in the coalition agreements a promise to enact
this bill. So given the substantive nature of this bill, as a lot of
submitters has already mentioned, I think the government needs
specific democratic mandate from the electorate to enact
this bill. So I would recommend putting this bill on hold until the
government has sought such mandate in the coming election.
So thank you very much.
Thank you, Ling. I will just see if any members have a question for you.
Does not appear to be the case. Thank you so much for your written submission and
joining us this afternoon as well.
Members, our next submitter is not here at present, so we are going to move
forward to Robert, and if they turn up, then we will go back to
them. So we'll just have Robert promoted.
Hi, Robert. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We have read your written submission. You have five minutes.
We do ask that you leave some time at the end for questions.
We see you've got yourself on mute.
If you wouldn't mind just unmuting so we can hear what you have to say.
Over to you.
We can't hear you, Robert, if you are trying to speak.
Okay. While we try to see if Robert can sort
out his sound issues, we might see if Vernon is
online.
He is. Fantastic. Hi, Vernon. Thank you for joining us.
Let's see if we can get your sound issues-- oh, great.
We can see and hear you. That's fantastic. You have five minutes.
We've read your submission. If you can just leave some time for questions, please.
Over to you.
Kia ora koutou. I'm an associate professor at the
Faculty of Law at the Auckland University.
Before I joined the academy, I was in private law practice 14
years as an RMA lawyer with clients covering the whole field,
major emitters, environmental groups, crown entities, infrastructure providers, and
others. So at Auckland Law School, I teach public and environmental law.
As noted in my submission, I was one of a group of practitioners and
academics asked to provide input to this idea of a
statutory bar on climate tort claims in July of last year, and
I've included in an appendix to my submission key points
from a briefing paper that I sent to officials.
If the committee hasn't looked over it already, I would ask you to do so.
It won't take long. It sets out the substantive reasons why
I think the amendment bill misses the mark, why the
fear of allowing the Mike Smith case to go to trial, the frankly
hyperbolic and implausible disaster scenario pitched by
Fonterra today is misplaced, and why, in my view, the
best way to proceed would be to let the case go to trial.
As Cody said, let's see what the judge says.
And as Sam noted, it's always open to Parliament to respond
legislatively once the outcome of the case is known.
Fonterra is not going to go bust. Parliament would not let
that happen.
But to stop the case now in its tracks would remove what should be
seen as a brilliant opportunity for the government, for you as
lawmakers, to address what I describe in my submission as a
major information asymmetry between large emitters and
regulators to secure robust information about the
ability of large companies to reduce their emissions, the kind of
information that you really only get through the discipline of a court hearing,
with briefs of evidence sworn under oath, lawyers from both sides
cross-examining witnesses, and the cold logic and the scrutiny
of an independent judge delivering a reasoned ruling.
But I don't want to use any more of my five minutes on substance.
I'd like to talk about process, and I'd like to talk about good lawmaking.
One of the major contributions of the coalition government this term has been to
put the process of lawmaking under the microscope.
National and ACT's coalition agreement included a joint commitment to
improving the quality of regulation by increasing
transparency and accountability of lawmakers, and this culminated
in the passing of the Regulatory Standards Act last
year. Of course, there are different views on the RSA, and it's
not perfect by any means. But it tries to impose a
discipline on lawmaking, setting down in a statute a
set of principles for responsible regulation, touching on rule of law,
preservation of property rights, obligations for good lawmaking that I
highlight in paragraph 6.4 of my
submission. The RSA doesn't just list these
principles. It puts in place process requirements to make sure
that these norms of good lawmaking are complied with.
So the chief executive of the sponsoring government entity, the Ministry of
Justice here, has to produce a consistency statement
testing a bill against each of the principles, and then the
minister has to respond to that statement.
And third, a new entity, the Regulatory Standards Board, is
charged with assessing bills against the framework.
Now, has that happened here? Well, no, not systematically or
publicly at least. And that's because those process
obligations sit in a part of the Regulatory Standards Act that came
into force on the 1st of July, and the amendment bill was
introduced two days before on the 29th of June.
The process obligations conveniently don't kick in.
The machinery for good lawmaking championed by National and ACT,
passed by Parliament, doesn't apply because the amendment bill
now before you was slipped in two days before the opening whistle
of the RSA regime. Now, that doesn't stop you as committee
members from playing your own role in this lawmaking process.
Whether or not a majority of the committee agrees with my and
others' substantive concerns with the bill, I urge you to
seriously consider whether you are in a position to recommend that the
amendment bill be passed. Without the benefit of an
independent assessment of the amendment bill's consistency with the
principles of responsible regulation in the RSA, there is a
strong case, in my view, for recommending that further consideration of the bill
be delayed until that process has occurred and the outcome
made publicly available and reported to the committee. Kia ora.
Thank you, Vernon. We have time for one quick question from Dr. Deborah Russell.
Thank you, Vernon.
In the papers that were released alongside when the bill
was
tabled in Parliament,
we got access to the advice that had been given to the minister, including
consultation with experts like you and others.
But the
way it was reported was in terms of some people said this, some people said
that. We couldn't get a sense of the weight of evidence on either side.
Do you have any insight into what most
constitutional law experts would have said or what the weight of evidence was
around this proposed legislation?
Yeah, well, look, I can't speak for others. I can only speak for myself.
But my strong sense is that from a constitutional law
perspective, there are serious shortcomings with the process that
has been adopted by the executive branch in relation to that bill.
From my perspective, speaking with colleagues, there are serious concerns about
the constitutional propriety of this bill, the interference
with live court proceedings, interference with rules of good lawmaking as
I've described and as I say in my submission.
So although naturally there's going to be a range of views on this, from a
constitutional and public law perspective, there are serious problems with the
bill.
Thank you.
Thanks, Vernon, and thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We really do appreciate it.
Kia ora.
Okay. Now, members, we come to Robert.
Robert, we can see and hear you this time, which is fantastic.
Good.
We have read your submission. You have five minutes.
Please do allow some time for questions.
Thank you. I'm a retired English solicitor.
I'm not in practice, but I have practiced for 50 years, and some
of my work was concerning European law, so I thought
I'd stick to that.
The
basic point I want to make is that if this bill goes through and
tort, this tort is not actionable in New Zealand,
plaintiffs who want to sue New Zealand companies will go
forum shopping
And they will get a
ready response from other jurisdictions if there is no
remedy to be had here.
What the
international norm will be in relation to the particular tort of
emitting greenhouse gases is yet to be determined.
It will emerge.
But we do have the European
Community's Directive
2024/1760, which
requires a company of a certain size in
the EU to take steps to
identify its adverse impacts to the environment,
including by way of climate change, and to do what it can to
minimize them. And that includes
pressing other contractors in its chain of activities to
do the same. Now,
New Zealand exports a lot of stuff to the European
Union, and it is extremely likely that European companies doing
that will be subject to the European law.
So there's a ready forum for disgruntled people going to be
available in 2029 when
this comes into force. So my essential point is that
this bill is going to be ineffective
to get the result that is required.
There is also the liability that it's going to be
repealed. It's not a popular act. There are constitutional
objections to it. The interference with live
litigation, as the last speaker mentioned, is
constitutionally wrong. I can't think of a British government
that's done it since
James I tried it on in 1607. But
this government has done it twice.
The first with the
Credit Contract and
Finance Act of last year,
and now this one, and this is not a good look.
New Zealand should not be telling the world that politicians
can be persuaded to interfere with live litigation here.
That is the essence of what my paper says.
Fantastic. Thank you, Robert. I will look to see if any members have a question.
We do, from Dr Deborah Russell.
Thank you. I wonder if you'd just like to remind the committee what happened to
James I?
James I was newly come to the Scottish throne, and he tried to try a
case himself. He said, "Well, I'm a king.
I'm a perfectly sensible bloke. I'll try this case." And he
did. And the Chief Justice
didn't like that, and
judicially reviewed his decision.
Judicial review being the modern term for it, but he just simply struck out the
King's decision, and the King was terribly upset and said, "This is treason."
And the Chief Justice said, "Well, you may be the King and you may be terribly
wise, but you're not a lawyer, and decisions shouldn't be
made by politicians or people like you
who don't actually do it for a living." And the King backed off,
and I don't think any British government's tried it since.
And certainly I don't think the New Zealand government should be doing this.
Thank
you.
You've got a perfectly good set of judges.
You're a respected common law jurisdiction.
You really can't not have a tort dealing
with this important issue.
Thank you.
Thank you, Robert. Appreciate you joining us this afternoon and for your written
submission as well. Thank you very much.
We now come to Jane Kelsey. Jane, great to see you and have you with us.
We have you down for five minutes. We have read your submission, but please
take it from here.
Kia ora.
I'm a retired
Emeritus Professor of Law from the University of Auckland.
My areas of specialization include
law and policy, Te Tiriti o Waitangi, and international trade agreements.
So firstly, I'd like to reinforce the points that have been made about the
constitutional significance of what is being done here, both in
terms of Te Tiriti o Waitangi and the balance of powers,
but also the impacts on
future measures on the climate crisis.
Because the time is short and time to analyze the bill has been
exceptionally short, I just want to focus in particular on the
trade agreements area.
In my opinion, this bill puts the Crown in
breach of its commitments,
certainly under the Trade and Sustainable Development chapter of the free trade
agreement with the European Union,
with potential implications as well that I haven't been able to examine
in depth on the free trade agreement with the United Kingdom.
But also potentially raising investor state
disputes if the right to sue is reinstated
at the detriment of an
investor that has access to ISDS under one of New
Zealand's agreements, such as Canada under the CPTPP.
So let me just explain what I think the
implications are that the committee needs to
consider here, which are not just legal, but they are
reputational, they are diplomatic, and they're potentially
economic.
So as a context to the issues in the
EU FTA,
in particular in Chapter 19,
what we've seen from the current government is a series of
aggressive measures that have wound back
cumulatively the commitment
of New Zealand to the NDCs and obligations under the
Paris Agreement We've also seen in this
legislation, in particular,
an attempt to reduce risks and create incentives for investors,
including foreign investors,
to the detriment of climate action.
That approach,
evidentially,
has been pursued despite advice in the regulatory
impact statement.
The regulatory impact statement recognizing that the Crown has not met
its treaty obligations and not met the quality
assurance criteria that are required for such
legislation.
It also comes in the wake of the
non-disclosures of the Official Information Act information from
the Prime Minister's office.
This has real consequences in terms of the obligations,
in particular under Article 19 (2) of the Trade and Sustainable
Development chapter of the EU FTA, what we call the
non-derogation or the non-regression rules, which is
basically not weakening the current levels of protection
afforded in environmental law in order to encourage trade or
investment, and not through cumulative
actions weakening the commitment
of New Zealand to achieving its Paris objectives.
The fact that the advice has, in fact, on the agreements has been
redacted from the risks suggests that there is a lot
of smoke to go with the fire.
So
I want to link my submission to another submission that you
have
received from Fernando Hernandez from Both Ends in the
Netherlands.
And this shows us where
this potential breach may lead.
Both Ends is a member of the domestic advisory group
established under the New Zealand EU FTA.
The domestic advisory group has a
responsibility to oversee the implementation
compliance with the Trade and Sustainable Development chapter
in that FTA.
The
EU's domestic advisory group discussed New Zealand's
backtracking at its recent meeting in May,
and they reminded
the European Commission that New Zealand had in fact supported
at the United Nations,
the endorsement of the ICJ's advisory
opinion in relation to climate change, and hence the relevant
jurisdiction.
Now, under that chapter,
the domestic advisory group can lay a formal
complaint through what is called the single entry point.
It is pretty clear, I think, from the interventions that we've
seen, that whilst the European Commission
itself may not challenge New Zealand's
non-compliance with that chapter,
civil society groups in Europe may well do so by
initiating a complaint through the single entry point under that
chapter. That will have significant legal, diplomatic, and
even economic consequences if this
act proceeds, because a breach can, in
relation to the Paris obligations, even lead
to the reduction or suspension of New
Zealand's tariff concessions under the agreement.
And so I want the committee to be very well aware that if
this bill passes, it will
likely have very significant consequences.
Thank you, Jane. Really appreciate your submission.
We've got time for one question from Huhana London.
Kia ora Jane. I just wanted to follow up with you from a Taha
Maori perspective and around the Te Tiriti breaches that you've
referenced and the risk that this
bill poses to the Crown Maori relationship-
Mm-hmm
... as well as the ripple effect that this decision will
have around lawmaking and the judiciary moving forward.
Kia ora, Huhana. Yes, as you will know, I've been an
expert witness in the Waitangi Tribunal's climate change
inquiry, which has been looking,
on behalf of Nga Toki Whakairereranga, specifically at the
implications of the trade and investment agreements, both the
ISDS and the fact that these commitments New
Zealand has made include commitments
that relate to its obligations to Maori,
both in terms of process and substance in
relation to the climate crisis. And the fact
that the risks made it clear that, certainly
in terms of the process, this bill
was non-compliant with Te Tiriti, but also the
fact that the litigation that Mike Smith is
bringing is sourced in Tikanga and sourced in the Crown's treaty
obligations. And so I would expect,
going back to my point about the domestic advisory group
process in
the
EU, the equivalent domestic advisory group here, which
has Maori members on it, including Tania Poture
from Nga Toki Whakairereranga, that those issues
will be provided as supplementary
to whatever action or complaint is taken
in the European Union.
Thank you, Jane. Really appreciate you joining us this afternoon and for your
written submission as well. Thank you.
Kia ora.
Members, we now come to Dr. Dean Knight. Dean, we've got you for five minutes.
We've read your submission. Over to you
Kia ora to committee. As you'll know, I'm a professor of law at
Te Herenga Waka—Victoria University of Wellington, specializing in
constitutional and government law.
And can I start by saying that it goes without saying that under the
principle of legislative supremacy, Parliament has the authority to
legislate to override the common law as it seeks to do so
with this bill here. The question, though, for the committee and the
House is whether the exercise of that legislative authority is
appropriate, wise, and properly respects other
constitutional principles and traditions.
My submission is that it
does not, and the bill should be rejected or amended, especially
to carve out and save Smith's current proceedings.
And the two points that I make are interrelated, one on matters constitutional, one
on the underlying policy.
From a constitutional perspective, and I start with those concerns,
nullifying Smith's current common law claims is objectionable,
constitutionally objectionable, because the retrospective effect of nixing
the claims undermines the rule of law, because interfering with the
judicial process in this way is contrary to the separation of powers and
breaches the principle of comity.
Because taking away Smith's day in court is contrary to his right to justice,
and because not preserving the fruits of any victory is contrary to the usual
traditions of fairness as reflected in our practice of legislative
design and quality. And as an aside, if this bill was introduced two
days later, once the Regulatory Standards Bill had taken effect, as Professor
Rye explained, we would have had a very grim consistency accountability
statement admitting to breaches of the principles of the
rule of law, good lawmaking, and responsible regulation.
Now, if I turn to the policy underlying the bill, the putative rationale is
weak and premature.
Claims of a need to override the common law to ensure regulatory
coherence and to confirm the executive and the legislature's
role of developing and setting and implementing regulatory policy
are, in my view, dubious and overstated.
The sure point is that legislation and the common law can generally,
and can in this case, work in tandem.
Concurrent legislative and common law regulation is not unusual, and I
instance a couple of examples in my written
submissions. And importantly, too, here, the current statute
regime does not cover the field or speak to the
damage to individuals the common law claims seek to
address.
In any event, the nature and reach of the current common law claims are not yet
known and still face some hurdles to be realized, and you've heard some
about that earlier. The strongest prospects, in my view, lie with the existing
and well-established tort of public nuisance, as addressed heavily by the
Supreme Court in its ruling. I think the so-called novel claims of climate
change caused loss has very low prospects for success.
And you've heard also about the prospects of different relief from earlier
submitters. And here I caution about being distracted by the novelty of the
latter. I think that's a red herring.
The principal basis of the claim is in public nuisance and involves the
application of preexisting doctrine to past facts in
the usual way that the common law adjudicates in
tort claims.
Importantly, the weak and, in my view, wafer-thin policy
basis for nixing claims means there is insufficient
justification for departing from usual constitutional
expectations about not legislating over top of live
court proceedings, and in my view, the bill should be rejected.
But if not, as a minimum, Smith's current proceedings should be excluded from the
proposed statutory bar. And I've also floated if that's done, whether
the statutory bar itself should be time-limited in order to allow the effect
of Smith's claim to be reconsidered once it is
determined. Finally, can I close by recording my concern about the
expedited lawmaking and select committee process?
It's shoddy lawmaking, unjustified procedural and
participatory shortcuts without justification.
That has become all too common, and I think are a stain on our
democracy. Kia ora.
Thank you very much, Dean. First question from Carl Bates.
Thanks, Chair. Thanks, Dean. In your experience,
what would the cost of a court case like
this generally be to the defendants?
Oh, it's been over two decades since I've been in practice.
The costs will be commensurate with
the degree of the claim, the complexity of the claim, and those sorts of
things. I couldn't offer a view on that.
Okay, fine. And in your understanding of the sort of outcome that could
be achieved if the defendant was to lose, what do you see as the
potential costs are to that company?
I don't know. I mean, you've heard some
earlier submitters talk about the
likelihood or the possibility of particular remedies being
granted or not. There's obviously the hurdles of liability first.
I don't know. We don't know because that hasn't come to pass.
It's all premature. But I expect that
it's not as grave as some of the
hyperbole that's been suggested here earlier.
Okay. The final question. If-
Yeah
... people know those things, then is it entirely appropriate
for Parliament to say, "We don't want to take this risk.
We don't want this effect to occur on the New Zealand economy,
even if it's slim"? And there's two very different sides to that argument.
Isn't it entirely appropriate for Parliament to say, "We're going to remove that
risk so that we can actually focus on doing the work to reduce climate
change effects in New Zealand?"
I guess my submission is that the constitutional
costs of doing so well outweigh that risk And the
best thing is for let the case to run, and then
allow the courts and the parliament and the executive be in
dialogue about the nature of responsibility for these types
of liability.
Thank you, Carl. We'll go to Dr. Duncan Webb, and that'll be the last of our
questions.
No, thank you. I really only have one question.
It's around the
idea of a citizen having the right to litigate
a claim in the civil courts and the concept of a
right to justice. You alluded to it, but I think it's actually at the
core of your objections. Can you just expand on
the concept of a right
to justice as a foundation of the rule of law,
and why this case is particularly problematic?
Yeah, well, I think it is one of those high points of the
right to justice, and that's part of the rule of law, the ability to
go to an independent courts to ask for the law to be
tested, to be adjudicated based on past facts.
That's a fundamental
feature of our rule of law, ensuring that we're a rule-abiding
society and so forth. And it's been fundamental.
I know that,
for example, when the
Labour government legislated
away the foreshore and seabed claims several
decades ago, that there was quite a bit of opposition from
the parties in government who are now promoting this bill.
Right.
So it's a well-understood principle that there is a procedural and
substantive aspect of the ability of someone to go to a court and ask,
the law should be supreme and should be applied here.
So what constitutional position we ended up with if governments of any color
legislate to
whenever they don't like a piece of litigation?
Well, it becomes lawless.
Because the
law that can be applied will be the whims of Parliament.
And one of the ideas of the rules of order of the system is we have a system of
laws that should be faithfully applied, and people should have the
benefit of that and the benefit of processes like independent courts that
allow that to be adjudicated and help will
be applied.
All right. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Dean. Really appreciate your written submission-
Thank you
... and to us this afternoon as well.
Members, we now have a break till 2:50, so six minutes, and I'll see you back
online for our submissions from Dunedin Museum of Natural Mystery.
All right. Welcome back, members.
We have the Dunedin Museum of Natural Mystery,
and we have Bruce joining us.
Bruce, if you are there, we will just promote you. Fantastic.
Bruce, we have you down for 10 minutes.
We have read your submission, so please do leave some time at the end for questions
as well. But over to you to begin.
Okay. Everybody, can you hear me?
We can.
Okay. So thank you for allowing us to speak.
So,
I think you've read our submission that you know we're a small charitable trust
and a philanthropic organization based in Dunedin that supports climate action,
conservation, and scientific communication, and our committee
includes university academics and professionals.
So we are rejecting this bill in its
entirety and asking for it to be withdrawn
immediately. In our view, the bill is completely inconsistent with the
Crown's responsibility under Te Tiriti.
Climate damage is not distributed equally, and I think we all know that, and that
Maori communities, low-income households, children, and future
generations are going to bear the disproportionate harm from the
emissions that they are least likely to contribute to and cause.
This litigation, brought by Mike Smith, currently focuses on the major emitters,
as we all know, including Fonterra, and that seeks to test whether those
causing or contributing to that harm can be legally held accountable.
And we believe that they should be, and that Parliament should not shut down
this question in advance.
Can I remind everyone that New Zealand declared a climate emergency in
2020, and this has not yet been rescinded, and that New Zealand still
remains a party to the Paris Agreement.
Yet the worst feature of this bill is not merely its inconsistency.
It is that the bill attempts to insulate the major emitters from ordinary
legal accountability precisely as the scientific evidence of
climate and ecological breakdown is becoming ever more severe.
The emergency is already here. We cannot
infrastructure or resilience our way out of this endlessly worsening
climate emergency. As the media and the
politicians would have us believe, there's no quick fixes here.
We're in dire straits.
Adaptation is essential, but at the moment, every ton of additional greenhouse
gases that we're putting into the atmosphere makes that adaptation harder, more
expensive, and in some places, like around the equatorial regions,
impossible. The human consequences aren't abstract.
In 2026, the World Health Organization reported that heat had
killed 200,000 people across the European Union
and associated countries in only four years, with nearly all those deaths
considered preventable. And that's the World Health Organization saying this.
Children are already being harmed.
Britain's most senior pediatrician warned that the climate crisis
poses an existential risk to every child through heat, air
pollution, extreme weather, illness, and lasting mental health effects.
In July 2026, with that massive heatwave in Europe we've just had,
classrooms exceeded 40 degrees and pupils suffered
fainting, nausea, headaches, and heatstroke.
One primary teacher described children lying on the floor and said most of
the children were calling for their mommies and daddies.
There was no learning, just surviving the best that we could.
So the climate crisis is part of an ecological overshoot,
an economy which is using more energy, land, and materials and
producing more waste than the Earth can regenerate or safely absorb.
Our economy cannot remain secure while its biophysical
foundations are collapsing around us.
The Institute and Faculty of Actuaries at the University of Exeter warned that the
climate and nature shocks
Could cut global GDP by 50% between
2070 and 2090 under current trajectories, alongside mass
mortality, displacement, and state failure.
Conventional models understate this risk because they fail to capture the cascading
breakdown across food, water, health, infrastructure, finance, and
governance. The point is that not every worst case outcome
is certain, and that's what we're arguing about.
The point is that the consequences are so large, the warning signs so visible,
and the potential damage so irreversible, that a responsible government must as
act on this risk and not wait for certainty after the harm has occurred.
This bill is moving incredibly, exactly
in the wrong direction. In any rational business engineering or public
health context, a risk of this magnitude would
trigger stronger duties, closer scrutiny, and more
avenues for accountability, and not less.
It would not trigger legislation designed to remove one of the few remaining
avenues through which affected people can ask a court to examine
responsibility for foreseeable harm.
What we would like the committee to do...
Sorry about this.
That's okay.
Is recommend that the Climate Change Response Tort Liability Amendment Bill
not proceed, but be withdrawn in its entirety.
At a minimum, the committee should refuse any provision that respectively or
prospectively extinguishes climate-related common law claims,
restricts the court's ability to develop tort law, or grants major greenhouse
gas emitters exceptional protections unavailable to other
actors whose conduct creates foreseeable harm.
The government exists first and foremost to protect the public, not to protect
powerful commercial interests from scrutiny.
Preventing people, iwi, and communities from taking major emitters to court for
damages to health, property, culture, and ecosystems, and the life of
future generations is morally indefensible, and we urge
you to reject this bill. Thank you.
Thank you, Bruce. I will just look to see if there are any members who have
questions for you.
Does not appear to be the case. Really thank you for your recent submission and for
joining us today as well.
Thank you. Thank you very much.
Thank you, Bruce.
We now have Casey Chambers who's going to submit to us.
Casey, we have you down for five minutes.
We have read your submission. Please do just leave some time for us at
the end. And we're just going to promote Casey.
Apologies, Mr. Chair, it just looks like we need Casey to accept the prompt to
become a panelist.
Okay. Thank you, Femka. Casey, if you can hear us, you just need
to accept to join us as a panelist
so that we can hear from you.
Perhaps she's not able to do that at the moment.
Is Carwyn with us yet, Femka?
Yes. We have Carwyn here. We can promote him through.
Yes, please.
Hey, Carwyn. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We have read your written submission. We have you down for five minutes.
Please do leave some time for questions. Over to you.
Well, tēnā tātou.
So I am opposed to this bill, and there are lots of reasons
for that, but I think there are kind of two areas
of major overarching issues with this bill.
And first is the fact that the bill is designed
to protect the short-term corporate
interests of greenhouse gas emitters at the expense
of the well-being of current and future generations of New
Zealanders.
And that, of course, is obviously hugely concerning.
But we shouldn't even need to be getting into a discussion about
that because of the second area of concern, the second
issue,
which is about the retrospective nature of this
bill, in particular, the fact that it's cutting off a case which
is currently live.
And I think that does
really needless damage to confidence in the
rule of law. And you'll see that that's where my brief
written comments were focused.
Now, I should say that
my written comments were brief, because partly
the select committee already has before it all the
reasons why this bill should be rejected.
You've got policy advice from the Ministry of Justice that's referred to in
the
departmental statement. You've got the regulatory impact statement,
which all actually make it plain that, first of all,
there's no real evidence of any impact on business confidence,
and but also even if there are some benefits
to this kind of statutory bar, which itself is, of course,
highly contested, then any benefits would be
outweighed by the impact on confidence in
regulatory stability. And so the government's own officials have said
this. And my written submission primarily draws on the statement
made by the New Zealand Bar Association, which also articulates the
concerns about the rule of law, the impact on the separation of powers.
Previous submitters refer to the Regulatory Standards Act,
but I don't think you even need to go there because, in fact, of course, the
Legislative Design Advisory Committee guidelines also set
out all those principles of good lawmaking that government ought to
be following
And so there are also obviously concerns about whether
this will meet the government's Treaty of Waitangi obligations,
and by which, of course, I mean that there's no way that this fulfills
Treaty of Waitangi obligations.
And
ministers had a choice. They also had all this information before them.
They had a choice to base their decision
about whether or not to progress this bill on evidence and reason, on principle,
but they've chosen not to. They've chosen not to follow advice of their own
officials. They've chosen to follow a pathway that was
lobbied for by commercial interests,
and there hasn't been real transparency about that.
And I think you as a committee actually have an opportunity here
to show that you're going to stand up for the interests of New Zealanders.
You're going to stand up for fairness instead of allowing
big business to call the tune to the detriment of
all of us. And so therefore, I'd encourage you to recommend
that this bill not progress any further.
Thank you, Cowan. We do have a question from Camilla Belich.
Thank you very much for your submission.
And given your extensive legal expertise, I
wondered if you could perhaps answer, we've heard from business about
one of the key reasons for the timing of this case being in their mind
appropriate is business uncertainty.
And I just wondered if conversely there was legislative
or constitutional uncertainty created by
taking this step at this time while the case is still
active.
Oh, I think absolutely this creates much more certainty than,
than-- Sorry, it creates much more uncertainty
than it would resolve. Because
if you--
I mean, what
position does that place any of us in there?
We rely on an understanding of the certainty of
what the law is and that there be mechanisms held that account.
And if you take a case and suddenly partway through the rug is pulled from
underneath you,
then that creates real uncertainty.
None of us can then rely on our institutions
of law,
and in fact, it's very damaging to the rule
of law for this to be happening, and there's no
justification for doing that in this case.
There's also real questions about whether a statutory bar
would lead to more or less litigation around what the boundaries of
that are. So
what the government could have done was, in fact, either to wait for the
case to progress and see actually what the outcome was and work with that,
or it could have undertaken the work itself if it needed to set up a
review
like we did with ACC, like we did with defamation,
in order to ensure that there is proper evidence and substantial
reasoning behind these decisions that they do lead us to more certainty
rather than less.
Thank you, Cowan, and sorry members, but we have reached our time there with you.
Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon and for your written and oral
submission.
Kia ora.
Okay, members, we're going to go back to Casey Chambers.
Looks like Casey's accepted to be a panelist, which is great.
Casey, if you can hear us, we'd just love for you to unmute yourself.
We have about-
Hi, can you hear me okay?
We can. Great.
Perfect.
Have you down for-
Well, there we go
... five minutes. Please do leave some time for questions as well. But over to you.
Sure.
Well, thank you so much for taking the time to chat with me today and all
the people who are submitting.
So
I strongly, strongly, strongly, strongly, I can't say that
enough times, oppose the Climate Change Response Tort
Liability Amendment Bill. I mean, even just using the
word amendment in this situation, like the definition of
amendment is to make something better, to improve
something.
I do honestly not see how letting big climate
polluters off the hook
is making things better in any way, shape, or form.
Yeah, it's like
I'm just an everyday New Zealander.
I don't have a massive platform. I'm not part of an organization or anything like
that. But I have been to a number of climate change
protests, and the rhetoric that I get from even just
our local politicians
quite often is that it is your individual
actions as a community that will make a real difference to tackling environmental
damage and climate change. Basically putting
this idea of empowering the everyday
individual and the everyday citizen.
But when you're doing that while simultaneously letting
big climate polluters off the hook and not, like
basically they're not liable for any damage at all, even though they're the people
that are creating
the horrible change, that are causing the floods, that are causing
accelerated climate change,
more severe weather storms,
things of that nature.
Yeah, to let those people off the hook, it's incredibly insulting, to be
honest. And seeing your prime minister flying
in a helicopter over flood-damaged towns in Aotearoa, shaking a
few locals' hands and engaging with the affected public in an attempt to be seen as
compassionate, empathetic, it's not enough.
It's at best a vague, basic attempt at PR.
I will say, because the thing I wanted to touch on the most was
the dairy industry and the animal agriculture industry.
And something that I heard the last speaker say or a question that was
asked is that a concern was business uncertainty
in regards to letting Mike Smith's case go ahead
I'd like to challenge that.
We're seeing very much in recent years, the world over,
places like Netherlands, Denmark, South Korea.
Denmark and South Korea, as an example, their
governments have created plant-based food system
plans in order to tackle climate change.
The Netherlands has banned
meat advertising and fossil fuel advertising in public
spaces,
because they understand that the climate crisis is urgent, and if they want to be
leading in climate policies, and then you rent out walls to advertise the
opposite,
what are you achieving? It's just canceling each other out.
And in regards to dairy,
I recently went to a protest at one of the dairy
awards that was last year,
and I did a lot of research on plant-based
milks.
There's a guy in Hawke's Bay who's growing
kabocha pumpkins to make this amazing milk that has won
numerous awards globally and is marketed now
in Japanese retail store chains,
and has been extended to 5,000 stores across Japan, Korea, and China.
David Seymour very recently gave us the green light on being able
to open up more possibilities with hemp, and I think we
all know about the amazing qualities of hemp.
It can be used for
clothes. It can be used to make biodegradable plastics.
It can be used for so many things other than
just making milk or making food products, and those are
just a couple of examples.
Oat milk also in Southland is really taking off, which is really exciting.
Soy crops are being grown in Canterbury, and Canterbury
and Southland are the places in Aotearoa that are the
hardest hit in terms of
intensive dairy farming, and as a result, intensive
nitrate contamination.
So the whole idea of business uncertainty and that
being an argument to not let this case go
ahead and to let big polluters off the hook,
I think that honestly, it's
just an excuse for
politicians and for big business to keep kicking the same can down the
same road that we've done for years and years and years, and we're seeing that it
is not working and making things worse.
So
that's all I want to say on that today.
Thank you, Casey. I really appreciate you joining us this afternoon.
We have met the full allocation of your time, but we do appreciate both your
written and oral submission, so thank you very much.
Thank you. Kia ora.
Okay, members, we're going to move to Christina Hood, who's going to join us.
Kia ora. Thank you for the opportunity.
No worries, Christina. We have you down for five minutes.
We have read your submission, but please do leave some time for questions.
Yeah. So I'll keep it to a minute or so.
Just to
say this is a submission in my personal capacity.
I am scheduled to be an expert
witness in the Smith versus Aotearoa and Others
case. I agreed to give testimony on the issue
of the adequacy of New Zealand's response to
climate change, both our legislative frameworks and from a policy perspective,
and that's
where I want to focus today. I guess my
overarching comment is just that emissions cause
climate damage,
and whether we regulate them strongly or
weakly, if there are still emissions, there is still damage being
caused. It is a
really tortuous and interesting legal
question around
responsibility for those damages.
But I think that it's a reasonable question to
ask if regulators are inadequately regulating
climate damages, whether those who are still doing the emitting should
bear some of the responsibility. So it's a question, I think, which
should remain live and be worked through in the future rather than being
eliminated by legislation. But I will leave it at that.
Thank you, Christina. We do have a question from Dr. Deborah Russell.
Oh, kia ora, Christina. Nice to see you.
One of the arguments that the government is relying on here is that the
government
and the executive is taking responsibility for climate change through the
CCRA and through the policies they put in place, so there's no need for this kind
of tort action. Do you think the current government
is doing enough, both in terms of legislation and in terms of its actual
policies to address climate change?
There's two pieces to that, and I don't think it's actually about the current
government. I think it's just about the framework overall.
So the Climate Change Response Act doesn't guarantee any
particular outcome. It's a
framework within which
decision makers can act to deal with climate change if they choose to.
It sets up some incentives that kind of,
hopefully,
coalitions of the willing will choose to act, but it doesn't
require particular outcomes or enforce particular outcomes.
There is no enforcement. So if a target is missed,
the minister has to come to Parliament and make a statement to explain why.
That's it. There is nothing built
into it that guarantees a particular outcome.
There are lots of examples that you can point to around
that, and one of them, and I just point to this as an example,
the government's current emission reduction plan for 2030
The projections are that that will actually miss the 2030 biogenic methane
target. So we have a target to reduce biogenic methane emissions by 10%
in 2030, and the current plan is missing that.
And
they've
built that plan into their recent consultation on ETS settings, for
example. So, I
actually think it's a fallacy to claim that just the very existence of
this legislative framework somehow means that we are dealing with
climate change. It's how you apply it that's going to answer
whether it is adequate or not.
And that relates to where the targets are set.
Are the targets set to be truly in line with 1.5?
The Climate Change Commission has recommended much stronger targets, and that
advice has not been taken. And it depends on
are policies doing their job? And we know, for example, that the emission trading
scheme needs a significant upgrade to be able to do its job.
And then finally, in terms of responding to
the climate change, if we are going to walk away from a Paris
Agreement commitment by not
following through with the offshore mitigation which is required to meet that
target, then that has climate damages as well that are not being taken into
account.
Thank you.
And we have one final question from Rima Nakley.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Welcome, Dr. Christina.
I just want to ask, with respect to the extremely profound
subject of greenhouse gas emissions, and I respect the
advice that you've given over the years.
But is it
prudent to suggest that such a profound
subject, a framework for policy, should be made on a case-by-case
basis?
I think there are
huge gaps in,
if you're talking about the case-by-case in terms of the Smith case and using the
legal system. Is that the question?
Yeah, using the legal-- I mean, the court system, which is a very special
system, but for something-
I think-
... as complex as greenhouse gas emissions
I think if it were the case, I don't think
it's that helpful to think about hypothetical worlds in which things are
perfect. If we had a hypothetical world in which our legislation was
binding and it was fully dealing with climate change and all of
those things, then we would be in a very different place to the place where we are
now. I think the question is more that if
regulators are inadequately regulating the damages from climate
change,
what then? Because the damages are still real.
They are still felt by those who are experiencing the floods, the droughts, the
heatwaves, the disruption.
And I think it's reasonable to question to ask
whether and where responsibility should fall.
The Supreme Court seem to be quite skeptical that the case
might be successful, but I think it's
a good and reasonable thing to ask the question and allow that to play out.
Do we have any more time, Mr. Chair?
Just one short question.
Thank you. Thanks, Doctor.
But am I to understand that in the absence
of there existing a strong
policy framework from the current government or the government of the day,
then we default to this
decision-making via court cases?
Well, it's not my area, but my understanding is that
citizens have always had a right to,
when they are experiencing harm from others, to find ways to try
and minimize that harm. And if governments choose not to do it, then
it seems reasonable to see how that
harm can be minimized.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Christina. Thank you both for your time and for your recent
submission.
Thank you. Bye.
All right, members, we're going to go to Kaitiaki Whangaroa,
who are going to join us.
Just going to bring them online now.
Here we go. Hi, Bridget. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We have read your written submission. We have you down for 10 minutes.
If you're able to switch your camera on and unmute yourself, please do just
leave a little bit of time for questions as well.
Kia ora. Nice Manuel is actually speaking on behalf, and I'm
here to support her. Is she being led into the room yet?
She has, yep. She's just there now. There she is. She has unmuted.
Kia ora tātou.
We'll take, obviously, our submission as read.
Tēnā tātou. Thank you for the opportunity to speak to our submission today.
My name's Nice Manuel. Hiori Hau or Whangaroa, and I'm speaking on
behalf of Kaitiaki Whangaroa.
We are here to ask the committee to reject the Climate Change Response Tort
Liability Amendment Bill in its entirety.
Our central message is this: communities already living with climate harm
should not have the courthouse doors closed before the evidence is even
heard.
For Whangaroa, climate change is not a future possibility or an abstract
policy debate. It is being felt now in our rohe by our
whanau and our marae.
Nationally, about 750,000 people and
500,000 buildings worth more than
145 billion are already near rivers and coastal
areas exposed to extreme flooding.
In Northland, Te Tai Tokerau, climate projections show more
intense storms and rainfall events, hot days increasing from
about 25 days now to around 90 days a
year by
2019 and rising sea levels increasing the risk of
coastal hazards and erosion. We
see those risks locally in flooding, slips,
coastal erosion, rising seas, damage to infrastructure,
and increasing pressure on our whenua, moana, wāhi
tapu, mahinga kai, papakāinga, and mokopuna.
These are not only environmental impacts, they affect safety,
identity, tikanga, whakapapa, and our ability to
carry out our responsibilities as kaitiaki, as mana
whenua.
The bill asks Parliament to take an extraordinary step.
It would prevent affected people, iwi, hapū, whānau, marae,
and community organizations from asking a court whether
particular conduct that causes or contributes to greenhouse
gas emissions can give rise to legal responsibility.
That is not a small technical change, it is a blanket legal
shield. At the same time, New Zealand's own official emissions
data shows that gross greenhouse gas
emissions from industries and households were
78,778 kilotons of
carbon dioxide equivalent in 2023,
with industries responsible for nearly 90% of that
total.
In that context, communities should not be denied the ability to ask
whether serious climate harm can attract legal accountability.
The bill would decide before the facts are tested that
communities cannot even bring the question before a judge.
We are particularly concerned that the bill appears directed at
stopping our whanaunga Mike Smith's claim in Smith versus
Fonterra.
Mike is one of our kaitiaki of Whangaroa, and his longstanding mahi
within our community gives this issue real and
personal significance for us. In February 2024,
the Supreme Court unanimously allowed his claim to be
reinstated and proceed to trial. That does not mean he
has won. It simply means the courts should hear the evidence.
If major emitters have not caused legal harm, the courts can say
so. But Parliament should not step in now to prevent the
case from being heard at all. The retrospective effect of the bill
makes this even more concerning. It would reach back into active
proceedings that have not yet been finally determined, including
Mike's case. A person who has relied on the law, gone through the
courts, and reached the point where the Supreme Court has allowed a trial should
not have that pathway removed after the fact.
This matters because sea levels
around parts of Aotearoa have risen
about twice as fast in the last 60 years as they did in the previous
60 years, and NIWA has reported on this.
It weakens access to justice. That's the point.
It also risks undermining confidence in the ordinary role
of the courts. For Kaitiaki Whangaroa, this is also a Te
Tiriti, tikanga, and kaitiakitanga issue.
Our responsibilities to protect whenua, moana, awa, ngahere,
taonga, and whakapapa, and for our mokopuna are not
separate from law and justice. They are central to how we
understand harm and accountability.
Article 2 of Te Tiriti affirms tino rangatiratanga over our
land, kāinga, and taonga. A bill that removes legal
pathways for protecting climate-affected taonga weakens those
protections and makes it harder for hapū, iwi, and kaitiaki
to uphold tikanga relationships.
We also reject the idea that climate regulation means common law
rights must disappear. Regulation and court accountability can
work together. The courts are able to consider evidence,
tikanga duties, remedies, and the limits of tort law.
Allowing a case to be heard does not create automatic
liability. It simply preserves the right of affected communities to seek
answers. Our recommendations are clear.
Reject the bill in its entirety. Preserve Mike's
right to have his case heard and determined by the courts.
If the bill proceeds, remove its retrospective application.
Protect the ability for Whangaroa iwi, hapū, and whānau and
marae and kaitiaki to bring claims concerning whenua, moana,
awa, ngahere, mahinga kai, wāhi tapu, taonga,
tikanga interests, whakapapa, and future generations.
And ensure that any lawmaking in this area is consistent with Te
Tiriti o Waitangi me he Whakaputanga.
To conclude, this bill is not only about emissions,
litigation, or technical legal rules.
It is about whether communities already facing climate harm
can seek justice. It is about whether the courts can hear
evidence before rights are taken away.
We ask the committee to reject this bill in its entirety.
Ngā mihi nui ki a koutou.
Fantastic. Thank you so much for your submission.
I will just see if there are any members who have a question.
Does not appear to be the case. That is no reflection of the quality of your
submission, and so we really are grateful for you joining us this afternoon.
So, thank you very much.
Ngā mihi ki a koutou.
Thank you.
We're now going to go Family Estate of Hereditary Chiefs, and we're going to
have Hone Werahamo Pohepa who's going to be joining
us.
Hi, Hone. We have you down for 10 minutes.
Hopefully, you are able to hear us.
If you can just unmute yourself. We have read your submission, and
please leave a little bit of time at the end for questions as well. Over to you.
Oh, kia ora.
This submission
is
to oppose the bill
In respect of the narrative first in law,
first in time. First in time, first in law.
Tēnā koutou katoa.
My name's Hone Wirimu Hoeper.
I am part of a registry of plus 2.3
million land interest.
This represents the 1835, 1840,
family estate of hereditary chiefs of birth and tribal
nations.
I appear before this committee having been appointed to a voluntary
position as a scribe
at the 150th commemorations of the 1835 Declaration
of Independence in Waitangi on
the 28th of October 2015.
In my view,
this legislation
raises constitutional and treaty issues that deserve
careful consideration.
My submission is founded on the principle that the Treaty of Waitangi was
breached on the first day of signing
by replacing the 1835 flag
of King William IV, Protector of Maori Maritime Law,
with the 1606 Union Jack flag of Queen
Victoria.
Since this historical crime took place, a second
most historic crime
eventuated after the invasion of Aotearoa was in
1852.
However, I believe the 1840 Treaty of Waitangi
established an enduring relationship between the Crown
and Maori concerning the governance, protection, and
stewardship of the lands, waters, and natural environment.
Climate policy directly affects farewell forests,
waterways, coastal environments, customary
interest, and the ability of future generations to
exercise kaitiakitanga. For that
reason, I believe Parliament has an obligation to ensure the
legislation
affecting greenhouse gas emissions is developed consistently
with the principles of the Treaty of Waitangi
and with meaningful engagement with Maori.
I also wish to place on record my view that the
constitutional developments following the enactment
of the New Zealand Constitution Act 1852
fundamentally altered the relationship established
under the
treaty.
I recognize that this interpretation
is not accepted legal position of the Crown, but I
respectfully submit that these constitutional
questions remain unresolved for many Maori
and continue to influence discussions about treaty
justice and constitutional reform.
In my view, these historical matters provide important context
for considering legislation that affects long-term stewardship
of Aotearoa New Zealand's resources.
Accordingly, I ask the committee to ensure that the
treaty implications of this bill are fully examined.
Maori rights, interests, and responsibilities as kaitiaki are
given consideration. The bill does not diminish
existing treaty obligations, and Parliament
continues to engage openly on constitutional
questions arising from the Treaty of Waitangi.
The legal argument opposing the greenhouse gas
emissions bill. I oppose this bill because, in my view, it
raises constitutional and treaty issues that have not been
adequately addressed. So I leave it at that for now.
Thank you very much. I will just see if there are any members who would like to ask
you a question.
Does not appear to be the case, but we thank you so much, Hone, for joining us
this afternoon and for your written submission as well. So thank you for your time.
Thank you very much. Mā tō wā ki a koutou katoa.
All right, members, we will move to Deirdre.
Hi, Deirdre. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
Yes.
We have read your written submission. We have you down for five minutes.
Please do leave just a little bit of time at the end for some questions.
Oh, thank you.
First, thank you very much to the committee for putting in the time to
listen to all of us, and it's really important, and I appreciate the work that
you're doing.
I would ask you to reject this bill in its entirety.
I think it opens a backdoor bill to the concentration
of power, and so it would be
disingenuous of us to continue with it for a number of reasons.
New Zealand is famous for its relational law and its
connections and communication,
and also its relational approach to business.
But
what we're seeing here is a parasitical
business model,
and that is detrimental, especially in a country the size of New Zealand.
So small things can have bigger influences here than we
realize, and the long-term implications of those things are bigger
than what we realize.
We don't have a mandate for this. We don't have time to look
at the complexities around this to really properly
listen. And that's why we need to uphold the rule of law and
allow the law and the courts to do its job properly and
listen to all the
people who are called to speak, and they have the time and
energy and are built to get to the truth of what's going
on. Let them do their job and let us stand
back, and then if need be,
at the end of it then Parliament can step in if it's
absolutely necessary. But until it's done its job-
Thank you, Deb.
Pardon?
Carry on.
Oh.
So until it's done its job, let it run its course.
We are at the risk of breaking lots of international
law understanding and allowing
ridicule for New Zealand and wrecking our reputation
internationally, because we'll be seen as
a country where our politicians can be bought by big
business. And I'm sorry, I can't find a nicer way to say that, but that's
how it's been interpreted in the few discussions that we've had so far.
And also doing something like this under
urgency is
kind of disrespectful. We haven't got a mandate.
It isn't something that any of the elected parties stood on and that we've had
time to discuss, so therefore it would be respectful to step back.
We are only one of eight million species.
We are not the big be all and end all of everything, and nor is
business. There are other ways of looking at how we live our
lives and how we are going to
bring forth what needs to be brought forth.
And it also completely ignores the Treaty of Waitangi,
which is one of the founding documents here.
And if we're really wanting to work in a
collaborative, communicative world, we need to build our
relationships, not destroy them.
And so I would ask respectfully that you throw out this
bill and that we work together to
find cooperative, creative business solutions
rather than reinforcing parasitical business solutions. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Deb. Thank you.
I'll just see if any members have questions for you.
Does not appear to be the case. Just wanted to say thank you so much for your
written submission and for joining us this afternoon as well.
Okay. We are going to move to Tony Ward. I'll see if Tony is online.
All right. I think we're just trying to sort Tony out at the moment, so we're going
to go to Alyssa.
Hi, Alyssa. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We've got you down for a five-minute submission.
We have read your written submission,
but please do leave a little bit of time at the end for any questions the members
may have. Over to you.
Tena koutou, tena koutou, tena tatou koutou.
This amendment is an attempt by our government to stamp its
own authority above the Supreme Court, and
it's therefore unlawful.
This is one of many actions taken by this government
to remove existing legislation and
initiatives that aim to reduce New Zealand's
greenhouse emissions.
It is particularly disturbing that media uncovered
that briefings to Parliament were directly written by
New Zealand's greatest emitters.
Good lawmaking incentivizes best outcomes.
By protecting business from any liability for
significant emissions, there is no
incentive for any behavioral change that
may result in emission reduction.
If significant emitters were penalized
according to their impact, then reparations could
support our climate response,
making New Zealand more resilient.
In its eagerness to be seen as good for business, this
government prioritizes short-term financial
gain without demonstrating responsible
oversight and protection for all
life and future generations.
Humans are already impacted by climate change.
We see that people are needing to relocate because of
destruction from weather events of greater ferocity
associated with climate change.
With our human ability to modify habitat,
we are one of the world's most resilient
species.
But with our capacity to create emissions,
we are one of the most harmful.
Climate change, the poorest
people
and the least resilient species
will struggle the most and have the worst
outcomes.
So if as humans we continue with unfettered emissions,
many other life forms will disappear as they,
unlike us, are unable to go
elsewhere or adapt to environmental change
This is expected to include crop foods, and
it's likely to result in significant
starvation events for ourselves and for all
species.
As a result of the things I've shared with you, I request you
withdraw this bill and enable the Mike
Smith climate tort case to proceed.
Thank you for this opportunity. Any questions for me?
Fantastic. Thank you very much. I'll just look to see if any members of the
committee have questions for you.
Does not appear to be the case. Obviously, no reflection on the quality of your
submission, and we really appreciate you joining us this afternoon as well, so
thank you.
Thank you.
All right, members, Tony Ward has joined us, so we're going to go to Tony.
Hi, Tony, thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We've got you down for a five-minute submission. We have read your submission.
And please do just leave a little bit of time at the end for us to ask any
questions.
Okay. I don't want to reread or represent my
petition. I just want to
highlight what I consider to be the most important issue going
on here.
And that
amounts to the
legislation giving the minister the right to make sole
conditions.
That's the first thing. The second thing is that this
bill itself is only in existence
because corporate companies
contacted the government, exerted their,
I wouldn't say right, but their ability
to
manipulate and
present legislation
without the public knowing, and then going on
to present legislation which reaffirms that and puts the
decision-making process into the hands of the minister.
I see this as a complete violation of
equality under the law.
It means that corporate organizations have immediate
ability to change and modify and present and
organize legislations that ordinary citizens like myself don't
have. And I find that a completely unacceptable and
anti-democratic thing to do.
Other than that,
the legislation itself is a backward step, I think.
It
removes all kinds of opportunities for the Maori
community to have input,
something that we've built up over the last 40 years.
I came to New Zealand in 1942, so I've been here 44
years,
and I'm proud
over that time to have been a part
of the building of a bicultural society
that I think most New Zealanders are proud of.
This bill removes that. It's a backward step over and
above everything else.
So I'm quite happy to answer questions if you have them.
I don't want to talk about my
written presentation. I've done that. You've seen it.
And I just wanted to reaffirm the two most important things.
Fantastic, Tony. We appreciate you joining us.
We do have a question from Carl Bates.
Yes.
Thanks very much, Chair, and thanks, Tony, for your
submission to this committee today.
You've highlighted this issue around, or perceived issue,
around the way parliamentarians become aware of
legislation. And as an elected MP, I'm dealing, even
today, with suggestions from
constituents and businesses in my community about changes they should see in the
law.
Mm.
Why is there any problem with businesses and
constituents and voters approaching politicians and
proposing changes to the law?
Nothing. The only thing that's wrong here is the lie.
They did it secretly. They did it behind doors.
The prime minister denied ever having seen it.
I find that really hard to believe.
Either he's incompetent and doesn't know what's going on in his own office,
or some other thing is going on.
So that doesn't change whether or not the law actually needs to change.
Oh, I think-
It doesn't change whether-- Sorry, I-
Sorry. Go on. Go on.
So that doesn't change whether or not the law actually needs to change, doesn't
change
whether or not it's an appropriate issue to raise, and doesn't change
whether or not Parliament has the ability to change it.
Your only concern is that there was a
miscommunication around the process-
No, that's not my only concern. My only concern is that what is
happening is a withdrawal of democratic rights for every New Zealand citizen.
And we will be unable
to challenge any company that comes along to do any dreadful thing
in New Zealand. No member of the public will be able to challenge that,
and I really object to that.
Okay.
Fantastic. Well, thank you very much, Tony, for joining us this afternoon and for
your written submission as well. We do appreciate it.
That's okay.
Okay.
Yeah, thank you.
Thanks, Tony.
Couple of our next submitters aren't here yet, but
Kat is here yet, so we're going to jump to Kat.
If we can just promote Kat,
please
Good afternoon.
Thank you for being with us early. We
do appreciate it. We like it when people turn up nice and early.
We have you down for five minutes. We have read your written submission and just
leave some time for questions, but over to you.
Sure. Thanks very much.
My name is Kate McInnes. I am professor in the School of Biological Sciences
at the University of Auckland. I'm also a lead author for the Intergovernmental
Panel on Climate Change Assessment Round Seven, which is happening now.
As a member of
Working Group Two, I've been compiling information on the climate change
impacts, vulnerability, and adaptation options for Aotearoa,
New Zealand, and this includes assessing policy.
I don't speak on behalf of the IPCC today, but I have drawn on the
knowledge that I've been developing through this process to come to my
conclusions, and I strongly oppose this bill.
I have three main points to raise today.
The first is that extreme events are going to continue to get worse.
The second is that there are also a whole lot of hidden climate change impacts that
we're just really not thinking enough about.
And the third is that the current policy options are not fit for
purpose.
So first, climate change is here and now.
We will continue to see devastating impacts of extreme climate events, including
cyclones, floods, droughts, fire weather, and heat
waves here in Aotearoa. These cause economic and
non-economic losses. In the worst case scenarios, we see loss of
human life. This is absolutely tragic, and we saw this in January this year in
Mount Maunganui when the landslides occurred in January.
Other non-economic costs include impacts on health, culture,
identity, social cohesion, biodiversity, and ecosystems.
And let's talk about economics, because that seems to be a big focus here
this afternoon. Earlier, we were given the number of
$21.9 billion over five years as being the cost
or potential cost of this
court case, and that number was given by Patricia Green, I believe is the
counsel for Z. So that's the number she gave earlier this afternoon.
If we compare that to the cost of Cyclone Gabrielle, Treasury
estimated that cost $14.5 billion,
and Auckland Council estimated a $4 billion cost for the Auckland
anniversary floods. Together, those are almost the amount, just
those two events, almost the amount that the
people are talking about in terms of what this might cost economically.
We are simply not factoring in the cost of climate change to our
communities, to Aotearoa. But of course, the events
that occur do happen naturally, but climate change is making them worse.
So attribution studies help us understand what that climate change
contribution is. And as an example of that, modeling
of two drought events that occurred in the period 2007 to
2017 showed that those drought events cost a total of
almost $5 billion to the economy, and the attribution analysis
showed that 20% of that could be put towards climate
change. So $1 billion of that $5 billion was because of
the climate change.
So as we move into the future and we have more and more of these extreme events, we
will also see them compounding. We will have floods following droughts.
We will have fires following droughts.
We will have
fire then flood. We will have successions of extreme storms, one after the
other, and we will not have time to recover between them.
The cost of these will mount and mount, and it will not just be economic, it
will be so many different things that we can't even really perceive just
yet.
So that's the extreme stuff. There's also the hidden stuff.
So an example of this is we had a warm start to winter this year, and this
can cause crop failures. So many of our important crops rely on
cooler conditions to stimulate flowering.
So the kiwifruit industry is particularly vulnerable to these warm winters.
The cost of that is enormous. Are we factoring that against these decisions that
we're making? Other vulnerable crops are apples, potatoes,
and a range of other foods. And these kinds of impacts are happening,
but just not given as much profile as the extreme events.
We also know that a lot of the impacts of climate change are quite complicated
and will exacerbate other issues.
So things like invasive species impacts,
pests and diseases are examples of those.
So coming then to the policy options, the emissions trading scheme
is the current kind of main policy lever that we have,
but that is not fit for purpose. What has happened is that we've seen a big
increase in planting of pines across the Motu because of that,
and pines are highly flammable. As the fire weather gets worse,
we will see worse fires across the country.
And modeling a couple of years ago suggested that within this
century, parts of New Zealand could see the kinds of conditions that
caused the black summer fires in Australia of 2019 and
2020. And these events could happen every three to 20 years,
depending on what part of the country you're looking at.
So these severe
fires are in our future absolutely and definitely.
And so all of the carbon that's tied up in those forests, well, most of it will be
lost back to the atmosphere. So the ETS is not doing what it's supposed to do.
And we also know that rural and Maori communities are particularly exposed to
all of this. And each of these events also then leads into
cascades of impact through natural systems, well-being of
individuals and communities, economic
impacts, and societal and community change.
So in conclusion, the current policies are not fit for purpose, and we
need every single lever available to us to be addressing this.
We need to be looking at how to be reducing emissions,
and we need to be holding corporations to account. Thank you.
Thank you, Kate. We do have time for just a couple of questions.
We'll start with Todd Stevenson.
Thanks. Thank you for your presentation.
Putting aside whether we agree with you about whether the current kind
of policies are working or not, but
You talked about attribution, and isn't that really one of the issues here?
We're all responsible for emitting greenhouse gases in some
way. And then, as you said, there's lots of complex
outcomes. So don't you think that's why it's
better to have a, whether you agree with it, and you've suggested there is more
that could be done in a
parliamentary government response.
But isn't that the reason it needs to actually be led by a government and by
Parliament, because it is we're all responsible, the
outcomes are complex, and attribution's very difficult?
The attribution is quite clear, and our largest emitters are the
main ones leading to that attribution.
So I think the largest emitters need to be held to account.
Are they being held to account? No, I would say
So you can tell me that you could
specifically tell me what Fonterra, for example,
attribution to specific events across New Zealand are?
No, you know it doesn't work like that, but we do know-
Oh, well, that's my point. Well, that's my point.
Yeah, but we do know that, say Fonterra, you've mentioned Fonterra, they are the
largest emitter. So therefore, they have a big responsibility to play-
Right
... in these attribution processes.
Right. But we can't attribute specific emitters to specific,
this is the issue, right?
It's not like the carbon comes out and goes, "Oh, okay, well-
No
... we have it, we're going to cause this one-
Right
... we're going to cause that one." We can look at proportionality, and I think
that's the important point here.
Yeah.
The large emitters are having the biggest impact.
We can say that for sure.
Right. But that's why I think that the government's
Thanks, Todd. We'll go to Dr. Deborah Russell.
Oh, thank you. And thank you, Kate, for all the work that you're doing.
The government, as one of its justifications for this piece of legislation,
says that it thinks we're better off having a legislative approach
and the executive doing the work to make sure we deal with climate change.
Do you think this government's record is sufficient to hold that up as a reasonable
thing to say?
Well, all I can say is from my analysis, we're not doing enough.
And so that's why I'm saying we need every lever that we can, and
let's not try and close off the levers that are available to us,
and that's why I think this bill is not appropriate.
Thank you.
Thank you, Kate. Really appreciate you joining us this afternoon, and thank you for
your submission as well.
Not a problem.
Okay, members, we'll go to our next submitter,
and we'll just see if the clerks can get them promoted.
Fantastic. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We have you down for a five-minute submission, and we have read your submission,
but please do leave just some time at the end for questions. Over to you.
Kia ora, can you hear me?
We can.
Beautiful.
Kia ora koutou. My name is Áine.
I'm a disabled person, and I've had a longstanding interest in the
intersections of disability and climate justice in particular.
But more broadly, just as a human being and
the wellbeing of our communities and the wellbeing of the taiao.
So I oppose this bill. I recommend it be withdrawn.
Reasoning for that is that I see it as a huge overreach
of government power,
which is not only about saving the government money, but also
saving large corporates money, even foreign-owned
corporates are in scope there, at the expense of our
taiao and our communities.
And so if there was ever an example of
government-sanctioned profit over people
and planet mentality, this would be that example.
I want to talk about where climate breakdown itself or climate change
comes from, because it's born out of the very same
ideologies that is giving a free pass under this bill
to corporates and governments
to pollute at will, essentially, without accountability.
So if we look back to the kind of ideologies that have
enabled climate change,
the sort of colonial plunder of and dispossession of land
is certainly one.
The extractive practices of the fossil fuel industry,
who have known since as early as about 1960s at
least
about some of the impacts of their actions, and now the impacts are
so clear to see, and yet
profit keeps being this kind of overriding
ideology above them.
So
that aspect of where climate breakdown itself came
from, that is being enabled by this bill. So this bill is not neutral.
It will enable more climate breakdown, essentially
because of its foundation, its philosophy.
Now, who is most impacted by climate change? We know this.
It's marginalized communities, it's frontline communities in the Global
South, in the Pacific, our disabled communities, indigenous
communities, rural communities,
and the taiao itself, obviously. And so all
of these communities and places are the ones with the most
to lose because of this
bill. We need
comprehensive climate legislation, yes, but it's the type that
would enable accountability,
that would be based on the wellbeing of the taiao, of te Tiriti,
and of human rights.
So in conclusion, a government that cares about its people should not be
afraid of accountability and should instead welcome it.
Happy to take questions.
Thank you, Áine. We've got a couple of questions.
We'll start with Ricardo Menendez March
Good. Anya, thank you so much for your submission.
Others have commented around the intent of this
bill. You've talked a bit about accountability.
What do you see are the risks for the government if this bill was to
proceed in terms of climate policy or impact on communities?
Even here in Aotearoa, we're seeing the impacts of
repeated flooding and repeated climate events
across the country. And so it's very
clear to see that already in terms of people's
housing,
people's wellbeing,
the actual taiao that people are really
connected to and connected to the whenua, particularly for Maori communities.
All of that is being undermined by climate change and
this bill is basically saying, "Well, that's fine."
And we do have time for one more question. I did see Dr.
Deborah Russell had her hand raised.
Oh, okay, she's quite all right. Thank you, Anya.
We really appreciate you joining us this afternoon. Thank you.
Thank you.
Okay, we're going to be moving to Energy Resources
Aotearoa with John.
Thank you, John. Great to have you joining us this afternoon.
We have read your written submission. We have you down for 10 minutes.
Please do allow a bit of time at the end for questions.
Great. Thank you, Chair, and thank you, committee, for the opportunity to speak to
our submission. I'm John Carnegie, I'm Chief Executive of Energy
Resources Aotearoa.
A little about who we are. We're New Zealand's peak energy advocacy
organization, representing the entire energy value chain
from producers to distributors, sellers, and users.
And we exist to enable constructive collaboration across the energy sector
as we collectively strive to address complex and
multidimensional issues such as climate change impacts.
Our members have a common interest in the robust public policy settings, and our
focus is advocating for systemic solutions across the
energy sector and the wider economy.
We support this bill. We agree that the proposed statutory
bar against private tort liability will provide the
legal certainty that domestic and international investors
require. These reforms strengthen the existing
regulatory scheme set out in the Climate Change Response Act,
the CCRA, and reinforce New Zealand's
bipartisan political commitment to clear
and stable climate change policies as set out in the
CCRA,
and on which the business community relies.
This predictability has in fact driven the sector to move
significantly towards emissions reduction.
We believe that climate change action is too complex and
policy-laden for the courts. Climate action
involves trade-offs between emissions reduction,
energy security, economic competitiveness, and affordability.
Deciding one company's share of global climate harm
involves complex choices about productivity, energy
use, emissions reduction, and how costs are shared
across
our society.
And those trade-offs require democratic accountability
and the ability to adapt over time.
Courts cannot provide either. It is a question that should be considered and
determined by Parliament, which is better placed to do so.
Parliament has done that through the CCRA and will continue to adapt
to those policy challenges through legislative mechanisms over
time and businesses both support and rely upon
its robust and reliable
statutory framework. If the CCRA needs
strengthening to address accountability for climate harm, Parliament
is the right place to do so with proper deliberation,
consultation, and democratic mandate, and that is exactly what this
bill seeks to do and why we support it.
However, while supportive of the bill, we do not think that it adequately
addresses the range of risks to business certainty.
Energy projects require large capital commitments, and the
assets often operate for decades.
Investors need to understand the obligations that will apply
before they commit time and money to proposals.
Unclear liability makes planning harder, raises
the cost of allocating capital, and weakens New Zealand's case for
investment against countries with more settled rules.
And that investment supports employment and the delivery of secure, affordable
energy.
A higher cost of capital either stymies investment,
creating scarcity, as we have seen play out in New
Zealand over recent years,
or if it proceeds, it costs consumers more.
Neither outcome is desirable, and the downstream impacts of this
uncertainty should be in no doubt.
Investment risk is not imagined, and we have experienced it
firsthand.
It plays out in the form of investor flight and permits
relinquished and the cessation of exploration drilling.
Reduced investment in natural gas supply that increases
coal-fired generation,
leaves less support for the development of new intermittent renewable
generation, and pushes electricity prices higher than otherwise.
These outcomes make emissions reduction and
electrification harder. But to reduce uncertainty
regarding climate change obligations, it is essential to
maintaining New Zealand's reputation as a stable,
rules-based destination for international investment and meeting
our climate goals. And we agree that the proposed statutory bar
against private tort liability will provide, to some extent, the
legal certainty that domestic and international investors need.
However, the bill does not fully address the risk of climate-related
litigation uncertainty for public decision-makers.
As seen in the Supreme Court decision Climate Clinic, there is
still uncertainty about climate change considerations when making
statutory decisions relating to businesses that are
otherwise acting under the CCRA, and we
urge the committee to close this gap.
And to do so, we recommend that one targeted amendment is
made to Section 3 of the CCRA.
This would amend the purpose provision of the CCRA to state that the
act provides New Zealand's complete regulatory
scheme for climate change, including activities that cause or
contribute to emissions or climate effects, where a relevant
statutory scheme is not otherwise explicit.
Now, we believe that this was Parliament's intention when almost
unanimously passing the CCRA into law, and our
proposed amendment is offered by way of a rectification
of an earlier omission.
Parliament would remain free to require climate change to be considered
under another law. However, any additional obligation would need to be
stated explicitly in that legislation.
Ministers and other public decision-makers could then apply the legislation
Parliament has passed almost unanimously without having to
infer further climate duties from the
CCRA.
Now, separately, we consider that the Climate Clinic case has also given
rise to other risks that Parliament should also address to
clarify the meaning of the benefit of New Zealand and the
Crown Minerals Act and limit that test to economic considerations.
However, this work goes beyond the immediate amendment sought through this bill.
So while we support the objectives of this bill,
Smith is a-- we support the objectives of the bill.
Smith is a novel claim, and we believe that Parliament has been
surprised with it proceeding despite there being a statutory
scheme to address climate change responses set out in the
CCRA, and additional changes required to meet the needs of our
sector and achieve the bill's stated objectives.
The proposed amendment to Section 3 would address the uncertainty created by
Climate Clinic.
Further climate obligations would apply only where Parliament has
expressly included them in the specific legislation.
Business and investors, along with public lawmakers, could then make
long-term decisions using the rules in the CCRA that
are clear before capital is committed.
That supports investment, employment, secure and
affordable energy, and New Zealand's progress towards lower
emissions. Again, I thank the committee for the opportunity to present our
submission, and I look forward to answering any questions you may have in the
remaining time.
Thank you, John. We've got a number of members with questions. We'll start with Dr.
Deborah Russell.
Oh, thank you. I'll actually just bump it straight to Duncan.
We'll go to the other doctor, Dr. Duncan Webb.
Okay. Thank you. Look, I was particularly interested to hear you say
you thought Parliament was the right place to do
this because of the process of deliberation and
consultation. I'm just wondering,
in terms of social license and so on, are you disappointed
that this is a bill that's had 10 days to submit, was
introduced under urgency, and has
been tarnished with some pretty
unfortunate lobbying, which was not
done transparently, as found by the Ombudsman?
Would you have preferred it to be done in a bit more
robust process?
Well,
Duncan, thanks for your question.
We believe that all processes should be robust and
provide sufficient time for due consideration.
Yeah. So do you think it would be a good idea if we took a bit more time over this?
And when you've only had 10 days to put together your submission, as has anyone
else, it's not really enough, is it?
Well, that's a decision for Parliament and the business committees of Parliament to
decide, not for me.
Well, you've just made the point that you want Parliament to do it because you
think it's a better deliberative mechanism, and it's doing this in
a very rushed process that's been heavily criticized.
Is it your view that this process is appropriate
for the step that's being proposed?
Look, Duncan, it's not up to me to form a view on that.
That's the decision taken by the business committees of Parliament.
But you-
Thank you
... you came here and said you think it's good process
Duncan, we've got questions from a number of other-- Excuse me, Duncan.
We've got questions from a number of other members, so I will share the screen.
I can see why he's avoiding the point.
Thank you. Todd Stevenson.
Thanks. Thanks, John, and thanks for your specific amendment that you put in your
submission. We'll make sure we look at that.
I have another question. It's really about this,
how basically international investors and some of the organizations you
represent view climate litigation risk, and really what
does that do to their investment decisions and thinking about New Zealand
if they're going to invest here?
Yeah, thanks. Thanks, Todd. Look, as a matter of principle, reducing uncertainty
is essential to maintaining our reputation as a stable, rules-based
destination for international investment.
And it's important to point out, meeting our climate goals.
So we agree that the proposed statutory bar against tort liability
will provide the legal certainty that investors need to consider,
and that the additional amendment we propose will do likewise for
public law. And of course- In the energy sector, this is particularly
relevant because it involves long-lived assets, and where capital
commitments are large, and where investors require
confidence that the rules governing
their obligations will not shift easily, quickly or, in fact, in
capricious ways. And these features are critical
to maintaining New Zealand's energy security and affordability,
and supporting the growth of renewables, and avoiding also the use of coal
while keeping downward pressure on prices.
But I think the point that I made in my submission is that investment loss
is not a theoretical consideration.
We've experienced it firsthand how easily New Zealand's
attractiveness as a destination
for international investment can be damaged.
When the offshore exploration ban was introduced in 2018,
investors fled. Highly prospective permits like
the Bach and Wiri prospects, which were being readied for
exploration investment, were handed back.
More coal is now being used to fuel our electricity sector.
Electricity prices have risen on average, causing factory closures and production
losses. This is what we have actually observed,
and that is what regulatory shock looks like in the energy
sector. And so climate litigation has already been treated as a
material investment risk globally for the sector.
And the other point is New Zealand doesn't operate in
isolation from those investor expectations.
Thank you. And we've just got one final question from Carl Bates.
Chair, would the--
Sorry, it keeps stalling. Chair,
thank you for that. My question is, would any
longer time for this to be going through Parliament have
changed your view or your submission, John?
Good question, Carl. No. No, it would not have.
Thank you.
All right. Thank you very much. And thank you for joining us this afternoon,
John. We really do appreciate it.
Thank you very much.
We now have Raphael online, who was supposed to be with
us a little bit earlier. So we're just going to promote him.
We're just going to go to Raphael before we go to Ted.
Hi, Raphael. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We have read your submission. We've got you down for five minutes, and if you can
just leave a little bit of time at the end for any questions.
And if you can just unmute and put your camera on, please.
There you go.
Good stuff. We're in your hands.
Are you there? Can you hear me all right?
We can.
All right.
Yeah, I just want to talk just
briefly on my submission and that
today.
Yeah, I
don't support the bill.
In terms of the transparency and
accountability, it's almost,
you could say,
another fast-track bill, basically.
To
me,
it's like another fast-track bill.
It's quite concerning
that,
it's just quite
concerning,
this bill, in terms of transparency and accountability
for
organizations or companies that
have investments in New Zealand. I think that's a--
Yeah.
What do you call it? I
don't agree with it for one
reason,
and I see this every day. It's like when I drive on
State Highway 1, I see
truck tire
tread all over the sides of the roads, and there's no
accountability for those companies that are driving those trucks that
allow all that tread to end up on the side of the road within our waterways.
And it's things like that where there's no accountability
and there's no transparency
through the different stages, whether it be through regional council, district
council. There's no accountability under the Resource
Management
Act for this mess that's been left.
This
country is endemic, basically, in terms of the environment that
we have in our country. It's not like any other place in the
world.
So, it's up to us citizens to protect
our environment in the best way possible.
And to have a corporate company like Fonterra
go through back channels and avoid the
actual
proper consultation and that, that's
backward
democracy, basically. We've gone
to the highest Supreme Court, and now we're going to a bill
to throw it all out
the window, basically, and allow this to continue.
Then, yeah, I just think that that's
not in the best interest of us
Kiwis that work on the front lines or that work in the trenches,
cleaning up the mess. I've worked on environmental projects, and
I'm working on catchments
with regional councils to deal with these sort of problems that are coming from
big corporate companies
like forestries.
Where I'm based at the moment, forestry is one of the biggest
here in the north is the forestry industry and the farming industry.
And a lot of that
slash, that black water, it ends up in our shorelines, on our
coastal lines.
And yeah, there's no accountability for any of those
companies that are producing that waste.
And we need some transparency there, and if we can't get it
openly and
transparently now, then there's no hope for us to
actually get some decent democracy happening
in terms of the environmental impacts that are happening on a
daily basis now with our country here in New
Zealand.
That's all I've got to say, guys.
Thanks, Raphael. I'll just see if there are any members who have a question for
you. Does not appear to be the case.
But really appreciate you submitting to us today, and thank you for your
time.
No worries.
Thank you. Okay, we're now going to move to Tony.
Sorry, not to Tony, to Ted. My apologies, Ted.
Thank you. And thank you for this opportunity.
Thank you for your patience.
We have read your submission, Ted.
We've got you down for five minutes, just leave some time for questions.
Over to you.
Thank you.
Thanks for this opportunity to speak.
Yeah, I think it's
kind of strange that while this is being framed as
providing business certainty,
what's actually happening is that the rule of law
is being broken. The concept in law that you
don't have retroactive legislation is being broken
by this. To me, it's the most profound
danger to business certainty that you could possibly
have.
It just seems really weird. I actually agree that we have major
climate change issues.
We have a lot of issues facing us.
But this constitutional danger of
retrospective laws
and
losing the separation of powers, losing the
role of the courts,
I think is a huge danger. It's a danger to business, and it's a danger to
everybody. It's a danger to us as individuals.
Yeah. The
extraordinary breadth of the statutory shield,
the new section
274 in the act that's proposed,
it's just over the top so far as I'm looking at it.
I won't get into the customary legal framework, but I see it that
we're in
one of the most complex, well, definitely the most
complex time in human history.
We have a monetary system that is based in scarcity.
It's based in value and exchange.
And if you think about that, if you think about oxygen in the
air, it's arguably the most important thing to any of us.
But in a market, it has zero value.
That wasn't an issue when the only thing that was abundant was
air.
But we now have automation and advanced AI,
and we now have the technical capacity to
meet the needs for a reasonable abundance of everything for
every person on the planet. But the economic system
requires scarcity. So that is the most profound
issue of our time. We have AI.
I think it very likely, probability greater than
90%, that we will have AI smarter than all of
humanity within the next three years.
That is a huge
issue.
We need to address climate change. It's a very real issue.
But we also need to have fundamental changes to our economic
system and the way we do business so that we have
a positive future for the environment,
for non-human life, and for all of humanity.
And I think this bill is entirely orthogonal to that.
I think it needs to be rejected in its entirety.
And
I don't think Mike's got a chance of proving tort law.
I think it's just
a crazy approach.
Yeah, I'll happy to take questions. Thank you.
Thank you, Ted. I'll just see if there are any members who have a question for you.
Doesn't appear to be the case, but we're really grateful for your written
submission and for joining us this afternoon. So thank you very much.
Thank you.
Okay, members, we are now going to have the
Environment and Conservation Organizations of New Zealand, Barry and Cath.
Hi, Cath. How are you?
I'm well, thank you.
Is Barry joining you?
Yes, he is.
Okay. We will have likely promoted him. We just need him to accept.
All right. What we'll do, Kath, we'll-
Then we'll get started anyway, I think.
We will. Yeah. We've got you down for 10 minutes.
We've read your submission, and just leave some time for questions.
Yes. Thank you very much, and we very much appreciate being
able to address you.
We've introduced
ECO in our submission. I would say, though, that we have
immense experience in this whole area of climate change.
We were alerted to it in the early 1980s,
and I personally was quite closely involved as a
senior lecturer in public policy and in economics in the development
of
the ETS and some of the other measures.
ECO thinks this bill should be withdrawn,
like many others.
The bill offends us, and it offends, in our view,
quite a number of constitutional principles, and it
also seems to reflect a willingness by
ministers to actually give in to vested
interests, and the sort of cloak and dagger-ish way in which
this proposal was advanced is pretty
offensive, in our view,
of large moneyed interests trying to get in on
the ground floor.
We
particularly oppose
the cloak of immunity that it offers to
everyone who is a climate polluter.
And we deplore the
intervention for its retrospectivity, but
also
for the fact that it
does not respect the separation of powers and the judiciary.
And that, in our view, is not acceptable.
We find that
it also would remove
the incentive to not pollute,
because there's no
holding to account via the courts for this.
I'm a public policy expert myself, and
it's apparent to us that the regulatory and policy approach
has not been strong-minded and has not worked.
And to remove the one final sort of
way of holding both the government and polluters to
account
is to leave us all worse off, but
also to open the door by others who would inflict
public harms
to
being lobbied for them to lobby
officials and ministers. We know that the officials in this
particular case said, "Don't do it.
This is not a good approach."
We know that the ministers have actually thumbed their
nose at that advice. Of course, they have an entitlement to
make their own views, but when all the experts
and all the
officials and the public are saying, "This is
grossly unfair and it's improper and it's
unconstitutional," then we
think the government should listen.
And we urge all of the
MPs from all parties, and we're nonpartisan,
to resist this and to say no to this bill.
It doesn't just deprive Mike Smith of
his right to pursue a tort, but it deprives
all of us, and it suggests that this
sort of underhand lobbying is going to
be a avenue that any polluter or causer of public
harm can
pursue. That makes the capture
of ministers by vested interests
particularly
likely for it to get worse, and
we
think it's inconsistent with Te Tiriti o Waitangi,
and
the sort of general lack of consultation and the lack
of
helping
or taking time to have hearings of length
is an aggravating factor.
We think the
idea that there should be only
one avenue for taking action
on climate change or for trying to regulate climate
change is completely wrong,
and we think that the bill has, and the authors of
the bill have not, in fact, picked up the many opportunities that
are available to reduce emissions,
which is something that they should do.
New Zealand is a signatory to the Open Government Partnership, which is
a multilateral agreement,
and there's nothing open about this,
and that
Open Government Partnership calls for inclusion and openness in
policymaking.
Yeah, we
endorse the submission by Lawyers for Climate Action,
and
also Jonathan Boston's
presentation is very good.
I'll leave it at that, and you may have questions.
Thank you, Kath, and I'll just see whether Barry might have anything
further he'd like to add.
Yes, thanks.
And thanks to the committee. Sorry, I've had a bit of problems connecting.
Yeah, this
bill actually opens a Pandora's box for future governments, which
probably the proponents of this bill
should think
carefully about, because it opens the opportunity for future
governments to basically
get rid of resource consents and other things that businesses may
have on the basis of
taking action which isn't the normality of
law, which is what this bill is removing.
Thanks.
Thanks, Barry. Thanks, Cath. I'll just see if any members have questions for you.
Doesn't appear to be the case. We're really grateful for your written submission
and for presenting to us this afternoon as well. So thank you very much.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thanks. Good luck.
Okay, members, Alastair is our next submitter, so we'll just
have Alastair promoted.
Hey, Alastair, thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We can see that you've accepted. If you just don't mind switching on your camera
and unmuting yourself.
We have read-
Yeah
... your submission.
Sure.
We've got you down for five minutes, so please do just allow a little bit-
That's all right, yep
... of time for questions. Over to you.
No, thank you for the opportunity to submit.
I'm submitting as a private citizen.
I'm not a member of any particular organization, but I
have a lot of concern about climate change and its effects
even now. We're seeing these around the country, and we're seeing
just how
destabilizing they are for small communities, for
example, rural communities like Ngaruewhenua on
the south coast of the North Island, where people rely on
their bridge
to
go into town. And
if the bridge is being sort of washed away,
what are they supposed to do? And really,
I think it's unsettling for people regardless of where they live in the country,
and hopefully we have a shared understanding now of what
the effects of climate change are going to be, because this is only the beginning.
I also have two young grandchildren.
I've had a lot to do with them just in the last
week, and when I look into their eyes, they are so
trusting and so innocent,
and I find it hard sometimes to
look them in the eye because I think, what
are they going to
ask me or about me and the action that we took
as polluters, as people who've caused a lot of the
climate change in the first place,
our relative inaction in trying to reverse it?
So that motivates me to speak
today, and I really want to be able to hold my head up to
those
grandchildren.
So on the one hand,
we see the threat coming down the line towards us.
On the other hand,
New Zealand has been noticeably slow in
adapting and responding,
both at a national scale,
but also individual businesses and
individual people. Of course, we do see people around us who
are responding and are doing things, and undoubtedly
some of the companies have things that they can point to which are
responses and
investment that is helping to
improve the situation. The trouble is the scale of it we haven't really
quite grasped,
and it's significant that New Zealand is--
We're still 20% above our
annual greenhouse gas emissions in 1990,
whereas, for example, the whole of the EU, 40% below.
They have managed to reduce their emissions
of 1990 until now by 40%.
We're on the wrong side of the ledger.
So that's something that we collectively need to take action on
at all levels, government,
companies and individuals. And from my reading of Mike
Smith's
bill,
rather,
the case that he's brought,
he's really just trying to point that out, and what he's asking for
is for the big
emitters of
greenhouse gases in New Zealand to get with the program in
terms of our Paris commitments
to be reducing their emissions of greenhouse gases
in step with that. That seems to me a very reasonable and
well-founded argument that he's put forward,
and it's one I think that really deserves to be heard by the public at
large.
In fact, he's speaking on behalf of all of us.
I certainly feel that he's speaking on my behalf, on the behalf of my
children and grandchildren, but also I think all of us as private
citizens. This really does
affect us all.
And so to see him potentially being
silenced, even when the Supreme Court has given
him green light to proceed with this case,
seems to me would be to silence all of the people that he speaks
for,
and that really does undermine the kind of
vibrant robust discussion that we need,
especially when, as we've seen, New Zealand is
a laggard in the area of climate change.
As a country, we need to
pull ourselves together and to start pulling our weight.
And that requires each of the companies involved
to do the same. They need to be pulling their weight, or be seen
to be pulling their weight. That's something New Zealanders, I think,
inherently understand and respect,
and want to see that happen. So,
the government, therefore, needs to act in the public interest more broadly.
Whereas unfortunately, it appears to be siding with these large companies.
It has its own reasons for this, no doubt largely economic.
But the impression that is given is that they're
not on the side of ordinary people affected by it,
and that they are going over the top of the Supreme Court, which you would hope
would have
supremacy, if you like, in this area, that its judgment would be respected.
So for that reason, I really urge the
committee to think about this and to point
these things out to the government, because Mike Smith deserves to
be heard.
The case that he is putting is a case on behalf of all of us, and
not just one.
Thanks. Thank you, Alastair.
Really appreciate both your written submission and for presenting to us this
afternoon. We have reached the allocated time.
Yes, sure.
But thank you very much for coming before us this afternoon.
All right. Thank you for the opportunity.
Thank you.
We're now going to come to Environmental Law Initiative.
Hi, Eliza. We have you here on behalf of the Environmental Law
Initiative. We have read your submission.
We have you down for 10 minutes, and just leave some time at the end for questions.
Over to you.
Thank you so much.
And I'll try and keep this fairly brief and leave plenty of time for
questions.
So I'm here today representing the Environmental Law Initiative.
We're a small charity focused on improving the outcomes for New Zealand's natural
environment through stronger environmental laws that are applied
robustly.
I won't repeat my full written submission, but I want to focus on
three key areas. The first is the poor
law-making process that has been used in relation to this
legislation. The second is that the rationale is
not made out. And the third is some general comments on the role
of tort law,
and particularly in protecting matters of public interest, and the role
of Parliament in addressing the same matters.
So, beginning with the poor law-making processes,
my organization, ELI, had put in Official
Information Act requests regarding any meetings
that may have been had
on the issue of the Smith and Frontieris proceedings, and
we
did not receive the full information
that those meetings had occurred, and there were written materials provided.
And an ombudsman inquiry was taken out and
found in our favor.
In that context, it is tremendously concerning that there is such a short amount
of time allocated for the Select Committee to consider this legislation,
and such a short window for submissions and for submitters to be presenting.
And that alone is sufficient reason for the Select Committee to
recommend that this bill not be proceeded with, that if any changes are
to be undertaken, that it should require a longer level of
consideration.
I'm seeing a hand up. Do we have questions sort of as they come, or
also at the end?
We'll have the questions at the end, so just carry on with your submission.
Thank you.
And I think that's something that is very worthy for the
Select Committee to note. This is not a situation where something has been
considered thoroughly and there's been plenty of time
for public input. It has all been rather rushed,
with a fig leaf of rationale based on business certainty.
So I'll come now to that rationale, because I think this is an area
where it's really beyond spurious to
say that certainty requires such a
significant intrusion into the ordinary
processes of civil litigation,
targeting a particular litigant and preventing a substantive
claim from being heard after a Supreme Court decision said that that
claim should be able to proceed.
And the main thing that I think the Select Committee on this should be
cognizant of is that climate change itself creates a very
large measure of uncertainty. In order for there to even be a
slight chance of a tort claim succeeding, there has to be harm.
Now, the harm that is occurring is occurring due to greenhouse
gas emissions and a failure to bend those down sharply enough.
And it's happening already. It's getting worse.
We've seen just over this weekend, the residents of Wairoa having issues with
the river bursting the banks again for the second time in only the last three
years.
We're now at a point where I've actually lost count of the number of extreme
weather events New Zealand's had just this year.
And this isn't overstating it at all.
The level of harm is already really significant.
These events are happening
Faster and faster than most people anticipated would be happening by the mid-2020s.
So the question of whether any of that harm may give rise to
tortious liability is a live one, and that's a live question whether or
not Parliament enacts a statutory bar.
So by enacting a statutory bar, it's not creating certainty, it's just deferring
the point of time at which the courts are able to consider that.
And in a context where the opposition parties have already committed to repealing
the legislation, there really can be no rationale for this based on
certainty. Because what it does is it just sort of presses
pause on developing this through the courts and then reaching a point where
Parliament can create a considered response to address any of the broader
social or public policy implications of a finding of tortious
liability. So I think it's important to be clear that that rationale
is really full of holes.
The
third point I'll be making is around the role of tort
law and Parliament,
more generally. And I think this is quite crucial because the
minister's statements at the introduction of the bill and also the general policy
statement really presents it like this is some sort of exceptional
situation that we are facing, an issue being
addressed with the courts that is already being addressed through legislation.
It's not exceptional at all. It's quite run-of-the-mill.
Tort law usually proceeds in parallel to the development of
a more
sort of detailed and comprehensive legislative response on the same issues.
I point to several examples of that in my written submission,
including the
quite obvious and famous one in New Zealand of the accident compensation regime,
which we've got the most extensive bar on bringing a tort claim in
any common law country because we can't claim personal injury in New Zealand.
What we have instead is a comprehensive form of
cover for both accidental and
non-accidental injuries, whether or not they
would have been creating tort liability.
Another example is in relation to leaky homes.
The Supreme Court decision in Sunset Terraces found that there was
liability for building consent authorities.
And there's been several years of
genuine, deep public policy consideration on how best to address that.
But that's all in the context where the court has been able to consider the
boundaries of liability and then Parliament has been able to
take that as the status quo of the law
once there's been proper due consideration of it and then think
about the appropriate response. And so if we carry that across to an example
such as the present, what we would expect to see in a sort of an ordinary good
lawmaking approach is let this play out at the courts, and then
once there is a decision, if that gives rise to areas
which require a legislative or regulatory
response, that's the point at which it can be made with proper public
consultation.
Instead of really assuming that the
possibility of any liability attaching for climate
emissions,
in itself justifies preventing the courts considering it.
So I can see two hands up, so I will pause now, and take any
questions.
Thank you very much, Eliza. We'll start with Dr Lawrence Sun And.
Thank you so much, Chair, and thank you for that submission, Eliza.
I've got two questions. The first one is just a confirmation.
So based on your submission, in terms of the poor
lawmaking process, this also fundamentally challenges the
principle of comity and the rule of law.
Would that be in terms of the process?
I think it's extraordinary to see a Supreme Court decision that
says a case should proceed to a substantive hearing and then Parliament effectively
overrule that Supreme Court decision.
I think that's
quite out of step with the normal operation of the boundaries between the courts
and Parliament.
My second question, maybe you may be able to answer.
Earlier in the day, we've heard from Jane Kelsey around the potential
implications this will have to our NZEU FTA, which will have
tangible economic
impact.
What do you make of the idea that this potentially
violates some of our trade agreements?
Yeah. I think that's an important question.
So I think there's the EU FTA and there's also the UK FTA, and they
have very similar provisions around effectively
obliging both parties not to wind back any of their steps on
climate protection.
I think, and you know, New Zealand and the UK in particular, we're both common law
countries, so there's, I think, a particular issue with that one.
There have been a number of areas where the government has already wound back
climate, and we're now reaching, I think, a tipping point of cumulative impact
of that and potential action by either
the EU or the UK.
I think the key point there is that the economic harm that would occur to New
Zealand from any sanctions on our
exports of agricultural products, and
other products,
would far outweigh the cost of taking stronger action on
climate change. And in particular, this case doesn't create any immediate
costs to the broader economy. It's
costs to the litigants, obviously, but
there is really
no real risk in just letting it play out and then seeing what
sort of legislative response might be called for based on,
for example, areas that the court might
identify as being matters that Parliament should consider.
Thank you. And just a quick question from Dr Deborah Russell.
Thank you. Eliza, thank you for your
submission In the papers that were released with the bill,
we got a back trail on the consultation that the minister had engaged in, and it
was very targeted, selected consultation with some lawyers.
Were you amongst those people consulted on the development of this bill?
No, we weren't, and we weren't aware that it was being developed until the
information was publicly released,
despite our having an interest that should've been known to the
Prime Minister's office because of our AA requests, which were not completely
answered.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Eliza. Thank you for joining us this afternoon and for your
written submission as well.
Thanks very much.
Members, we're now going to take a break till 4:55, and then
we will come back for the last of our submissions for today. Thank you.
Right, members, we're into our last stint of public
submissions.
Clerks, if you can bring Samantha Reid in, please.
Hi, Sam. Thank you for joining us. If you're able to just unmute yourself
and switch your camera on, if possible.
Is my camera not on?
It's not, unfortunately, but we can hear you.
Can you see me now?
There we go. We can see you now.
Perfect.
We have read your submission. We've got you down for five minutes.
Just leave some time at the end for questions. Over to you.
Fantastic. Thank you.
Tena koutou i te committee.
Ko Samantha Reid aho. Nga mihi nui
kia koutou for hearing my submission today.
I won't repeat my written submission.
Instead, I want to speak directly to what this bill means for ordinary
people,
for our constitutional balance, and for the integrity of climate
governance in Aotearoa.
First, this bill removes the ability of people harmed by
climate-related conduct to seek redress.
That is not a technical adjustment to tort law.
It is a fundamental shift in how the state treats those who suffer loss.
When Parliament tells victims, "There is no pathway for you," it is
not regulating climate change, it is withdrawing justice.
In Te Ao Maori, we speak of manaakitanga,
kaitiakitanga, care, protection,
responsibility. A system that denies the right to be
heard does not reflect those values.
Second, the bill creates a constitutional imbalance.
Courts are not obstacles, they are partners in accountability.
Removing judicial oversight in an entire area of
harm is unprecedented.
It risks a precedent where Parliament can extinguish remedies whenever they
become politically inconvenient.
That is not the tikanga of our constitutional tradition.
Ko te tika me te pono, justice and truth require
that courts remain able to perform their role.
Third, this bill sends a troubling message about whose interests are being
protected. Communities facing climate harm,
Maori land blocks, coastal settlements, low-income
households are left without remedies.
Meanwhile, industries who conduct contributes to that harm
receive statutory protection.
That is not Te Tiriti o Waitangi in practice.
Active protection means ensuring vulnerable communities retain access
to justice, not removing it.
Fourth, the bill undermines public trust.
People already struggle to understand climate governance.
When Parliament removes the courts entirely, it signals that
accountability is optional for those with influence.
That corrodes confidence in both the legal system
and the democratic process.
Finally, I ask the committee to consider the long-term consequences
of climate change
demands--
So finally, I ask the committee to consider the long-term
consequences. Climate change demands courageous, principled
governance. This bill does not meet that standard.
It protects the powerful, abandons the
vulnerable, and weakens the constitutional safeguards that uphold the
rule of law.
I respectfully implore you to withdraw the bill in
full. Nga mihi nui.
Thank you, Sam. Now, I will look to see if there are any members with questions.
Does not appear to be the case. We're really grateful for your written submission
and for presenting to us this afternoon as well. So thank you very much.
Thank you very much.
Okay. Now we're going to have the Animal Justice Party, Aotearoa, New Zealand.
Great. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We have read your written submission. We have you down for 10 minutes.
If you can, just leave some time at the end for questions from any
members. Over to you.
Kia ora. Thank you, Chair. And thank you all for the opportunity to speak
today. I'm Karen Singleton. I'm the policy president for the Animal Justice
Party, and I'm joined by Danette Wirita, who is the co-leader for
AJP.
So I want to be up front, neither of us are lawyers.
We've approached this submission as lay people with expertise in
animal welfare, protection, and justice.
We also want to note that only 10 days were given for this submission, with oral
submissions called the very next day of it closing.
That's an extremely tight timeframe for a bill this
significant, and we don't think it really gave the public enough
time to respond properly.
So the Animal Justice Party opposes this bill and we call for it to be
withdrawn.
What stands out to us most is how broad the bill's protection is.
It doesn't just shield one type of emitter.
It protects virtually anybody responsible for emissions, including
government departments,
ministers of the Crown, foreign-owned companies
operating here. In substance, this bill protects
polluters at the expense of everyday New Zealanders who are left with
no way to seek compensation or hold anyone accountable for
climate-related harm.
Now, we've heard today a lot of submitters talk about certainty,
but there's no real certainty to be had in a world facing climate
crisis. What this bill offers might be certainty for a small
group for a limited time, but it's not certainty for the country.
From a justice perspective, what we do understand is this, what counts as
harm worth taking seriously isn't a fixed notion.
It's decided by government through regulation and legislation,
and those decisions aren't made in a vacuum The people and
industries with the most resources and influence often have the
greatest ability to shape where those lines get drawn, sometimes in
ways that keep their own activities out of reach of any meaningful
accountability.
This bill seems a clear example of that in action.
It decides a whole category of harm, harm caused by emissions,
will never again be tested in court, no matter how serious or
how clearly linked to a specific source.
That's not a small or minor choice.
It's a decision about whose harm gets taken seriously and whose
doesn't.
So courts exist precisely because law doesn't always keep pace
with harm. They're one of the few places where that gap can be tested.
This bill closes that door, not just for future cases, but for ones
already underway, like Smith versus
Fonterra, a case that's been going through the courts for a few years now.
We've also seen it argued that courts aren't equipped to deal with something as
complex as climate change, but our own Supreme Court has
already rejected that idea when it allowed the Smith versus
Fonterra case to go ahead. It pointed out that courts have adapted
before to industrial pollution, water contamination, multiple
polluters causing shared harm. It didn't see climate change
as fundamentally different, just bigger in scale.
So we don't see why that reasoning should change now.
And I'll hand over to Danette if you're there.
Kia ora. It's also worth remembering that a lot of serious harm
happens through completely normal, everyday, even legal business
practice. And many of today's business models have been built around
harmful environmental practices into how they operate as
standard, not as an exception. That doesn't make the harm any
less real, and it doesn't make the consequences any less foreseeable.
This bill looks, to us, like an attempt to run away from
accountability for that harm rather than face it.
Now, we care about this because animals, wild and farmed, don't get
a vote. They don't get a say in Parliament.
Climate change is already reshaping their lives, warming
seas, changing rainfall, shrinking habitat, and it compounds
other pressures that they're under, too.
The courts are one of the only places where harm to them and
to the environment they depend on can still be raised, even
when politics moves too slowly to act.
Removing that option doesn't make the harm go away.
It just makes sure that no one can be held accountable for it.
We'd also ask the committee to think about who this bill actually protects.
It's not about communities facing flooding or drought.
It's not about the insurers left holding more risk.
It's about the industry and companies whose emissions are the reason we're having
this conversation at all. Shielding the parties most responsible
while leaving everyone else to carry the cost doesn't strike me as
a reasonable use of Parliament's time.
So in closing, the question isn't whether Mike Smith will ultimately win,
it's whether he should be allowed to have his case heard.
If the defendants believe they've done nothing wrong, why not let the case be
heard? Why not let the evidence be tested?
Justice should be allowed to take its course.
Now, listening to Fonterra's submission today, it struck me that they were simply
arguing their defense. But this committee isn't a court.
If Fonterra believes their evidence is on their side, they should let
justice take its course and present that evidence at
trial. And is the possibility of
economic impact enough to stop a court case?
This assumes very blindly that the economic cost of
environmental harm doesn't matter, when in reality it could be
far greater. We ask the committee to think about your legacy
with this decision. Do you want to be remembered for preventing a court
from hearing evidence or for allowing justice to take
its course? Today it's climate change.
Tomorrow it could be something else, and it's a very dangerous precedent to
set. We'd ask the committee to think about what happens to the harm
that falls outside,
harm that fall outside today's law.
If this bill passes, there's simply nowhere left for them to
go. Given the short time that the public has had to respond, we
also ask the committee to consider whether more time and more
scrutiny is warranted before a change like this is
made. We ask you to reject this bill. Kia ora.
Thank you, Danette, and thank you, Karen, both for your submission.
We do have a question from Dr Laurence Sunam.
Thank you, Chair. Kia ora, Danette and Karen.
Thank you so much for your submission.
I'm really interested in knowing, in terms of the climate impact
on animals, and you mentioned farmed animals in your submission.
Would you, by any chance, have some key stats, for example, on the
recent harm, either
physical,
I guess, injury or even potentially death from recent
climate change weather events? Would you have any data on that
or know of any stats?
Not specifically on weather events, though they're
pretty common in the news at the moment.
So,
you can look at the news and see a weather event and
see the impact on farmed animals. I don't have those numbers on
us.
Thank you. Sorry. It was a very specific question.
No. Yeah.
It doesn't appear we have any other questions, so we just thank you both for your
written submission and presenting to us this afternoon as well.
Great. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you. All right, we come to Extension Rebellion Otipoti, and
we've got Jen. And Jen presented to us yesterday as well.
Great to have you back, Jen.
Hey, Jen. Nice to see you again. Thank you for being here.
Yes. Hello.
You know how this works.
Yeah.
You've got 10 minutes. Just leave some time for questions. Over to you.
Yeah. Thank you. I've come down with a bit of a cold since I talked to
you yesterday, but
I hope that won't stop me.
Yeah. Kia ora koutou. Ko Jen Olsen toku ingoa.
I'm opposed to this bill, and I'd like to see the committee recommend
its total withdrawal.
I was very disappointed to see that once again, the government has cut short the
time available for submissions on this bill, because I think it's very
important. And it's doubly disappointing that they appear to have
responded to requests from some of the subjects of Mike
Smith's case that's on its way through the courts to prevent
that case from being heard. I'm not a lawyer, but I don't consider
this to be a good example of justice in Aotearoa, and I know
a lot of the lawyers
don't think so either.
Tort law in New Zealand deals with wrongful acts where a party's
breach of duty causes harm to another.
And tort law is how the law develops to deal with new
situations in society. The climate crisis is not
exactly a new situation because it has been developing for many years,
but is newly recognized for the serious situation it is, and
our laws have not yet caught up with the urgent
necessity of a response. A small number of
companies in Aotearoa are responsible for a high proportion of climate
change and emissions. For example, the companies in Mr.
Smith's case are responsible for about one-third of our total
emissions, and there's no scientific doubt whatsoever that these emissions
are causing harm. These major emitters have knowingly
continued their activities, have not reduced their harmful emissions, and Mr.
Smith proposes that the law should provide a remedy, and that remedy
is a duty to cease their harmful activities.
Contrary to the claims of some members of the government, existing
climate law does not deal with this element of the climate crisis.
There's nothing to identify greenhouse gas emitters or major
polluters, and there are no laws requiring them to reduce their emissions
or to stop other harmful effects on the land or water.
Aotearoa has been relying on the so-called market influences in the form
of the Emissions Trading Scheme,
which has become totally ineffective for a number of
reasons, including the exclusion of agriculture
making up almost half of New Zealand emissions, companies being
given free units, and no effective cap on carbon units
when forestry planting is used as a substitute for actual
emissions reduction. So failure to reduce emissions has
left us with a massive shortfall in our obligations to the Paris Agreement,
made worse by this government backtracking on many policies
around emissions reduction.
We're entering uncharted territory in the climate and
ecological emergency that's now taking place.
Our government is not providing the guidance that is needed.
Instead, they're causing more uncertainty by backtracking on climate
legislation that was previously agreed under a bipartisan
agreement. So Mr. Smith's case is filling a
gap left by existing legislation and attempting to
compel major emitters to address their carbon emissions in a
meaningful way for the first time.
He also argues that tikanga Maori should inform how the law develops,
and the Supreme Court took that point.
Now, public nuisance is a recognized tort, and as a climate
activist, I understand very well the emissions of greenhouse gases that
we know are causing global warming, sea level rise, and climate
emergencies in our communities. They are a public nuisance
of the first degree.
Sea level rise is a major threat to many communities,
particularly in South Dunedin. I'm speaking to you here from
Ōtepoti, Dunedin. I've worked for many years in South Dunedin,
and there are people there facing having to leave their family homes
for good because of sea level rise.
And storms and unprecedented rainfall are becoming regular
occurrences. There's been a state of emergency almost continuously
somewhere in the country this winter.
Insurance becoming more expensive, hard to obtain, and
I think food supplies are very likely to be affected in the future.
Internationally, the climate emergency is hitting the Pacific Islands
particularly hard, and we'll need to provide a home for many
Pacifica who will lose their lands.
Europe has recorded more than 200,000 heat-related
deaths since 2022, and thousands
more reported during the recent extreme heat events.
Drought is a major cause of conflict in sub-Saharan Africa.
Flooding and landslides have made millions of people homeless in Pakistan and
Bangladesh. And this is at one and a half degrees of global
warming above pre-industrial levels.
If we don't make some real and drastic reductions in emissions of greenhouse
gases, we are heading for three degrees of warming.
Now, I can give you the scientific studies that
have analyzed 10 different climate models and
found that the majority of Earth will go past two degrees of warming by the
2040s, reaching three degrees maybe
the 2050s, 2060s,
and this comes from Stanford University, Colorado
State, the German Physical and Meteorological
Societies, work by James Hansen, the
Institute and Faculty of Actuaries.
And they have laid out a report stating what will
happen
when we reach three degrees of warming, which is going to be sort of
2050, 2060 if we don't act on what we've
got. They're saying that the global economy
will shrink by 50%. Now, it's interesting to hear
that some of the defendants in Mike Smith's case have been
talking about the economic impacts if they are made to actually
reduce their climate emissions.
I don't think it's reached as much as 50%.
That's what's going to happen if we don't reduce our emissions.
And not only that, they're talking about four billion deaths
worldwide, significant sociopolitical
fragmentation, failure of states, and
extinction events.
No government appears to have the courage to tell the truth about the climate
and ecological emergency, let alone to do something about it.
I can't believe that the response from this government is to pass a law
that protects emitters from accountability for the
damage caused by their emissions.
You will have heard it all, and you'll
know what the legislation is. So that means we won't be able to claim for
endangering or impairing life, safety, health,
property, or climate
change-related risks to a safe and habitable climate
system. Corporations, ministers, government departments, and
foreign-owned entities will all be protected from any legal
responsibility for the harm they cause.
I think Mike Smith should be commended for his work in finding a way to
make polluting companies finally face the
responsibility for the harm they cause and to stop polluting,
and for bringing Tikanga Maori into the picture.
The current capitalist political system, with its short-term
profit-based thinking, has brought about the climate and ecological
emergency we're now facing.
Colonization, capitalism, and climate change are inexplicably linked,
and our politicians are so embedded in the financial system and
tied to short-term electoral cycles that they're unable to
make the kind of changes that we need right now.
Climate change requires system change, and taking a
Tikanga Maori approach to developing some solutions to the
impasse that we find ourselves in might allow us to see things
differently.
Extinction Rebellion Aotearoa, New Zealand have always supported the concept
of participatory democracy, of te tiriti-based
citizens' assemblies like the Porirua
Assembly to bring mana whenua together with representatives
from our communities and allow everyone to be fully informed on the
issues around climate, emissions, and the future.
All the evidence from assemblies that have been held
internationally shows that ordinary people are not afraid to
face the difficult issues and make responsible decisions.
We would support assemblies being organized around the country, with the
results being adopted by local and national government.
This would broaden the debate about making the social environmental changes
we need and enable communities to make their own decisions.
Small countries like ours can make a meaningful difference to
emissions. Together, the smaller nations make up a third
of global emissions, and actually, as we know,
Aotearoa has high emissions per capita.
We have the ability to set an example that others could
follow if we had the courage to break free from the
influence of the big emitters.
Unfortunately, this law does not demonstrate that.
It demonstrates the opposite, and therefore, I urge the committee to
reject it in its entirety. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Jen. You have reached your full allocation of 10 minutes, and
so we really appreciate you spending time with us this afternoon and for your
recent submission as well.
Thank you.
Thank you. Okay, we're now going to have Jill Jackson.
Hi, Jill. Thank you for joining us.
If you can just switch your camera on and unmute yourself.
We have you down for five minutes. We have read your submission
already.
Please do leave some time at the end for questions. Over to you.
Kia ora, and thank you for having me. Am I the lucky last?
We've got two after you.
Okay. Well, anyway, I'm speaking as a
private citizen against the bill.
Everything I'm going to say has been said better by somebody else already,
people with more expertise. But I'm just going to make four
points.
I was a primary school teacher, and I've done my best over the last 40 years
trying to turn big ideas into small words.
So, here goes.
The four points I want to make is, number one, the bill I
feel is unfair.
The bill, number two, is rushed.
Number three, it's not really ready for
delivering to the public. It's undercooked.
And the last point, number four, is that it undermines our
trust in democracy the way it's being implemented at the moment.
So those are my four reasons for submitting.
It's unfair, I feel, because it appears that the
government is putting itself above the law, that if there's a
case that it doesn't like the look of, it's just going to change the law,
which shouldn't happen.
Also, there's got to be some way that an individual
can
get some kind of recompense if an individual or a business
is doing something to the environment that they live in that is harmful.
So that's the unfair part of it. It's rushed.
Climate response is an enormous issue that needs a
plan with everyone behind it. It shouldn't be a political
football.
It's about the survival of our grandchildren and possibly the whole
human race. It's just foolish to be
wittering over who's right and who's wrong.
It needs cross-party support,
public education, and possibly deliberative
assembly discussion,
so that we can transition away from the industries that are dependent on
fossil fuels or that are emitting greenhouse gases,
regardless of whether they're the backbone of our economy.
It's obvious that there's damage being done, and it's obvious that we're going to
have to transition at some point.
I don't think this bill is ready. It feels like it's been done in a huge rush.
Obviously, there's got to be some-- Well, we hope there's going to be some
liability that will be recognized in law for
damage by whoever, whether
it be a business or an individual. We need a national response
plan
with litigation
that doesn't have to be undone. This litigation is too rushed
and can be undone next time around.
It feels like it's being done so quickly that the whole issue
that needs discussion is being swept under the carpet, and then the
carpet's being nailed down, and it's just making a mess.
It's not helpful to do this at this point.
So that's the undercooked part. I think we haven't
discussed how we can transition our major industries.
You had some fascinating submitters talking about things like plant
milk and
hemp and other things that we could be doing.
And if you listen to people like Greenpeace who say halve the
herd and
talk about regenerative farming, not necessarily meaning that farmers
lose any money, there are ways around this.
And regardless
of people
kicking and screaming
about losing money, it has to be done at some point.
When do we start?
And my last number four point,
it undermines people's trust in democracy,
because things that are rushed
and done under urgency, sometimes at night, it does
sound cloak and dagger. It sounds
secret squirrel. It sounds like you don't want the light of day to
see it.
And so people don't trust the process.
And already we've got not enough trust in
democracy. So don't make it worse.
There's also been suggestion that advice has been taken
from interested parties to the exclusion of the
public. I don't know if that's true, but it certainly doesn't
help
us believe that this is the right thing to do.
So before we look at rushing a bill like this through, perhaps we should be
looking at regulating the lobbying and lobbying
by industry and maybe putting some sort of regulation in there
first. And my recommendation is that the Smith
versus Fonterra case be allowed to continue and the
bill be rejected entirely. And recommend everybody gets on
board with some kind of genuine climate
response survival plan that starts with something like maybe the
Fossil Fuel Treaty Initiative, where people have done a lot of work
on how to transition from industries that damage the
climate.
And that's my five cents worth.
Thank you, Jill.
Thank you.
We do have one quick question from Jamie Arbuckle.
Thank you, Jill. In your submission, you highlight the issue around
regional councils, and I'm wondering if, is that still a concern for
regional councils to be able to do their job?
I'm not sure whether-- I presume this
bill would prevent them from doing what the Gisborne
Council is doing to the forestry
people. I'm not sure, because I haven't read
the ins and outs, but I know that the Gisborne Council is managing to
get some recompense for the forestry slash and the damage that that's
done. So if this bill was to prevent that,
that would not be a good thing. But I'm not aware
of how it's going to affect them.
Thank you, Jill. Appreciate you presenting to us this evening and for your written
submission as well.
Thank you.
Okay, we're going to have Zero Carbon Nelson Tasman, Fred and
Paul.
Hi, Fred. Hi, Paul. Thank you both for joining us this evening.
We have read your written submission.
We have you down for 10 minutes, and please just leave some time for questions.
Over to you.
Thank you, Tom.
With me is Paul Martin, and we speak on behalf of Zero
Carbon Nelson Tasman Incorporated.
Our society's purpose is to build awareness of the challenges posed
by climate change and other threats to society and biodiversity, and
to develop, encourage, and inspire suitable responses to mitigate and
adapt to these, particularly in Nelson Tasman.
So, thanks for this important opportunity to present to you today, and we sure
appreciate your attention at the end of a long day.
In our presentation, we'll argue that the Tort Liability Bill sets an
extremely dangerous legal precedent in undermining the previous
Supreme Court decision and retrospectively eliminating Mr. Smith's current claim.
In the alternate that the government is asking us to rely on, current
climate change policies are reprehensibly inadequate in the face of a world
currently on a path to about 2.6 degrees warming
at 2100 if current policies around the world are
implemented.
In our view, the bill should be withdrawn and Mr.
Smith allowed to have his day in court.
So speaking in a little more detail,
first, the legal aspect, we aren't lawyers,
but we've been very impressed by the compelling analysis included in submissions
from
Lawyers for Climate Action and Jonathan Boston.
And we support the Lakandi submission entirely in arguing that
the rationale for the bill is flawed.
There's no risk of the courts developing a parallel and contradictory regime,
and there is no evidence that the Smith versus Fonterra proceedings have caused
business uncertainty
The bill undermines the rule of law, and it undermines the separation of powers.
The bill extinguishes Tikanga Maori conceptions of loss and likely breaches the
principles of Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
The bill is inconsistent with the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act,
and the bill is inconsistent with New Zealand's international obligations.
I beg your pardon. I should have passed over to Paul.
So Paul, would you like to carry on, please?
Sure.
So as Fred has mentioned, we support Jonathan
Boston's submission. Jonathan Boston,
if you're not aware, is the professor of policy studies at the
Victoria University of Wellington School of Government.
And one of his quotes from his submission is, "Moreover, the bill is
inconsistent with the government support several years ago for the International
Court of Justice to provide an advisory opinion on the legal obligations of
states to reduce greenhouse gas emissions under international law.
Why, for instance, is the ICJ competent to rule on climate change related
matters while our courts in Aotearoa apparently are not competent to do
so? Note too, that New Zealand was among the 141 countries that
endorsed the General Assembly resolution earlier this year, welcoming
the ICJ's advisory opinion. Put differently, the government
somehow saw fit to vote for climate accountability through legal mechanisms in
New York, but now wants legal immunity from such accountability
at home."
Thanks. And picking up next, Paul,
from Paul. We speak next to the manifest inadequacy of the government's current
policies in addressing climate change risk.
In the global picture, scientific evidence shows global heating is occurring
faster than previously expected.
Our world is now on the cusp of a 1.5 degree
global temperature rise. I'm hearing an echo.
Yeah, it's coming from Paul. So Paul, you can just mute yourself.
Sure.
Thank you.
Sorry about that.
Thank you. Some predict two degrees by 2040, unless urgent
action is taken
to change course. And even at 1.5 degree
C, we're rapidly approaching multiple earth systems
hitting tipping points that will transform our world,
with devastating and irreversible consequences for people and nature.
And examples of these are the Greenland and Western Antarctic ice sheets,
global thermohaline frost floor, and slowdown of the Atlantic
Meridional Overturning Circulation, easily spoken of
as AMOC.
These may seem far away, but because Earth's climate system is interconnected,
Aotearoa will not be immune to these consequences.
And for example, just to pick a piece out
of a paper published in March this year on the consequences of an
AMOC collapse,
this predicted Antarctic temperatures warming by around six
degrees.
So this is a collapse of the circulation in the North Atlantic, and this has
flow-on effects right through the Earth's
circulatory systems. And such change in the Antarctic is going to
cause immense changes in our climate here in Aotearoa.
We sense most of our political leaders are unaware of the scale of these risks,
and currently, our legislative framework and policies that we're being asked to
rely on are completely inadequate to address these risks in our view.
The government has dismantled many initiatives and programs to address climate
change.
Instead, for its primary program, it relies on an ETS that is not fit for purpose,
which is to drive down emissions. And germane to the bill,
it excludes agricultural methane and nitrous oxide.
Further, the government is on a path to default on our first nationally determined
contribution under the Paris Agreement.
This is our primary tool for influencing the world call to public
opinion
on whose decisions our future climate depends.
Further, the government lacks an effective climate adaptation response.
It's seemingly oblivious to emissions reductions being the first
tool in adaptation, and to research showing the global
economic losses. For instance, the global economic losses that can be avoided by
2100 with a 1.5 degree scenario
are estimated to be five times greater than the climate
finance needed by 2050 to achieve them.
And further, the government has just recently shelved the Climate Change
Commission's recommendation that a future Aotearoa contribution to
global action
is a net negative 20 million tons CO2 emissions equivalent
per year.
As a further comment, we believe this bill will cause further damage to New
Zealand's reputation with regard to climate and environmental issues,
and with respect to compliance with international rules and agreements.
Environmental groups have documented at least 35 ways New Zealand has
backtracked on established policies or undertakings,
particularly in climate change. It seems highly likely that each change, including
the current proposal, would increase that risk.
Paul.
So, in conclusion, this bill would remove, retrospectively,
the legal right of Mike Smith and of others to seek remedy through the courts for
the damages of the greenhouse gas emissions of major polluters in
Aotearoa on himself and his iwi, when the Supreme Court has
determined that indeed, he has this right.
So it's basically shifting the risk from the polluter
to the public. This would set an extremely dangerous legal precedent and
be an abuse of legislative power in undermining the Supreme Court decision
and eliminating the current and future claims.
Citizens will no longer have access in court to vindicate their legitimate claims
to damage by corporates through climate change emissions and other pollution.
This is a major erosion of citizen rights.
The government's program for addressing climate change is, as we have said,
manifestly inadequate and cannot be relied upon to address the
existential threats of climate change for our young people, for future
generations, and for biodiversity Please do the
right thing. Show moral leadership and recommend that this
government allow Mike Smith's case to be tested in court, as well as
further such cases.
And we welcome further any questions.
Thanks, Fred. Thank you, Paul. I will look to see if any members have
questions. We have one question from Dr Lawrence Sunan.
Thank you so much, Chair. Thank you, Paul,
and Fred, for your submission. I guess through your submission,
I'm curious to know in terms of the impact on whether you
think it would be
appropriate, considering the most egregious emissions,
particularly through agriculture.
It's through agriculture, but the price tag is being left picked
up by taxpayers broadly.
I'm looking at it specific from economic angle, but absolutely you are right about
the climate angle, environmental angle, and all of the other social costs.
But if you look at from that, do you think that'll be appropriate?
Do you think that should be appropriate?
You're on mute, sorry.
We could put the argument up that the polluter pays,
and I think that that's probably the best way of answering your question.
What we're seeing with this
bill is that
polluters effectively are being exempted
from
any action by citizens to address
the impacts on those citizens, and we're being asked to rely
on a government legislative and policy framework
that is just
inadequate for the task, and
in many ways is leaving the cost of that onto the
vulnerable, the people who aren't--
the poor,
the
people in less developed countries around the world,
and those are the ones who will be-- and Maori for that matter, too.
Those are the people who disproportionately will suffer for
this bill.
A quick sub. Do you think the polluters are currently paying?
I think when agriculture is completely omitted from the
ETS, that's a slam dunk argument.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Fred, and thank you, Paul, for both joining us this
evening, and for your recent submission as well. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Right, members, we come to our last submitter of the day, the Law Association of
New Zealand, and we've got Warren Pike, who's going to be submitting to us.
Hi, Warren. If you can hear us, we'd love for you to switch on your
camera.
There you are. Fantastic.
Hi. Good afternoon, everyone.
We've read your submission, Warren, and we've got you down for 10 minutes.
Off you go.
Yes. Well, I was listening with interest to the last presenter,
and
rather than start by summarizing our submission, I thought I would say
something about what really is at issue here.
What you have is a clash between
finding a solution to the problem of climate change.
And what Norman Kirk said when he was Prime Minister was what was important was
looking for a solution to a problem that would work, rather than arguing about the
problem.
So, the solution here is between a parliamentary process, a political
solution,
and it's an alternative solution that might rest in a court process.
And I think it's worth knowing what the advantages and disadvantages of them are.
I can summarize these by reference to two sets of Reith Lectures, and I'll just
read briefly some excerpts from Lord Sumption's Reith Lectures in
2019, where he made a couple of prescient points
which I think have to be considered here.
Before I turn to that, the way I'm seeing it is litigants seem to have a
great deal of expectation of what can be achieved out of a court
proceeding and tort to solve a global problem.
It makes no sense, and in my submission and the Law
Association's position is that Parliament can
legislate to solve this problem, and it can
exclude the courts from involvement in it as a matter of power.
The question is: should it do so? And these are extraordinary
measures here, depriving litigants of any rights to
access the courts.
Some things Lord Sumption said in his Reith Lecture in
2019 are regarded as inherently illegitimate.
For example, retrospective legislation,
obstructing access to a court,
acts contrary to international law and so on.
This does not mean that Parliament cannot do them.
It means that those who propose such things must squarely declare what they are
doing and take the political heat.
On the other hand, he went on to address the limitations of what
can be achieved in proceedings before a court.
The judicial resolution of policy issues
can undermine the single biggest advantage of the political process, which
is to accommodate the divergent interests and opinions of citizens.
Namely, this is my interleafing, trade-offs.
It is true that politics do not always perform that function well.
It may be that politics are not performing it well at the moment.
But judges will never be able to perform it.
Litigation can rarely mediate differences.
It is a zero-sum game.
The winners carry off the prize and the losers pay.
It is not a consultative or participatory
process,
it is an appeal to law.
The overarching message of the Law Association is, yes, Parliament
can do this, but it's far-reaching, it's unprecedented for the
reasons I've read out from Lord Sumption, and Parliament
must pause for considerable thought before
taking the steps that are proposed in the bill.
The retrospectivity and the
extinguishment of rights to access justice are particularly important
features to consider.
The association has suggested
an alternative,
that what could be legislated would
not be to bar all proceedings
but give defendants, such as in the Smith and Fonterra case,
a complete defense to claims if they can show compliance with the statutory
climate change regime.
Another option would be to preserve the right to sue in tort
for emissions that are non-compliant with the statutory
regime.
And I want to give an example from my own practice career a long
time ago, where I had a client who lived behind a timber treatment
plant that leaked chemicals repeatedly into their section,
ruined the value of their property.
The regulator took no steps over many years to enforce the
regulations to prevent the discharge of these chemicals.
They were able to sue and obtain a settlement nuisance.
Now, that shows you the value.
What we have here is we're taking away the rights of all
citizens to sue people who are causing a nuisance,
and to take any steps to make the regulator do the right thing.
And in the Law Association submission,
that is a very far-reaching step that Parliament should carefully think
about before taking it.
My neck's a bit that way as well.
Yeah.
I've only been lifting hay.
Now, my last point, and I can't see how much time I've run already,
and I want to leave some time for questions,
is that there's only been two judges who have ever given the BBC Reith
Lectures, and the first one was a judge called Lord McCluskey back in
1986. He touched on the same theme that I've referred
you to.
He said this about the law and policy,
which I think is important here. "The point about the development of the law in our
society is that the law givers,
whether they're judges or legislators, create general rules intended
to yield acceptable results in all foreseeable cases.
Then life throws up unforeseen cases, and either they or changes in
society's perceptions show that the rules are inadequate,
so they are changed. The courts are the laboratory in which the rules are
tested against reality and proved for social justice.
We can trust the judges to do that."
So with that, I'll take any questions.
Thanks, Warren. We have about three or so minutes for questions.
We've got Camilla Belich first.
Thanks very much for your
submission. Apologies for my voice. I just had two questions really.
The first one was,
in your submission, you indicated that you thought it was possible for the bill to
be drafted in a way that could achieve its aims, but by limiting
the effect to only what was necessary, and I think you
just gave a couple of examples in your oral submission as well.
So that was my first question. And the second question I have is, we have
had many submitters talking about how this bill
is necessary because it otherwise would create uncertainty for
business.
But from your submission, I take it that you think that this bill
will, by trying to get rid of uncertainty for business,
actually create uncertainty for citizens as to the law.
Well, I don't think it will create uncertainty for
citizens if it's passed in its current form.
It'll give them certainty that they can't sue anyone for this type of activity.
And what we're proposing is that the second look
be headed to try and preserve those rights to access courts
on the sort of suggestion that we've made.
I think the association can see the issue of
uncertainty for business, and it's an important issue, and it's a real
issue, because otherwise you're going to see claims coming riding over the hill
in unpredictable times and
from unpredictable litigants if something's not done to
regularize the situation. So yes, it needs a careful
look-
Mm
... and I think certainty is one of the factors.
Just to clarify, I was just talking about uncertainty as to what the law would be,
given
your objections to its retrospectivity and its
constitutional significance, not as to what the law is in relation to
climate cases.
Well, it looks pretty certain to me if it's passed in its current form, you can't
sue.
Yeah.
Oh, sorry, Camilla, you're on mute.
If the government changes the law in this way, how can citizens have
certainty as to what the law would be in the future, given that this is
retrospective?
Well, I'm not sure what your question really is driving at, which is
possibly why my answer didn't correspond with it.
Right. I took from your submission, which I read in quite a bit of detail, that
there was a significant objection to the proposals due to the way
that it essentially
challenged our normal constitutional conventions,
thus creating uncertainty for citizens as to the
workability of our law within its current form.
And so I was asking about that aspect of uncertainty, not about the
uncertainty in relation to the specific claims of climate
tort.
Right. You're talking about the broader
impacts here on lawmaking generally.
Well, I think the association's approach is this is extraordinary,
and it is
possibly a thin end of a wedge. The only other relevant one recently is the
marine and coastal area legislation, which was directed at a
supposed interpretation problem, but it also nominated
specific proceedings. That is a trend that the
association has identified that Parliament should be careful about,
because where's the endpoint with that?
So yes, there is uncertainty in terms of what Parliament may do in the
future.
Thank you. We've got time for one more question.
Who would like it out of Lawrence and Debra?
Debra can go.
Thanks, Lawrence.
It was a fairly straightforward one.
In the papers that were released when this bill was tabled in the
House, the minister's officials referred
to
some limited consultation that they had done with constitutional
experts and various
lawyers. Were you among the people consulted by any chance, or do you know
whether the Law Association was consulted?
I don't know the answer to that. I certainly wasn't.
Okay. No, we don't-
But whether the association was, I don't know.
Yeah, okay. Thank you.
I don't think there are opaque constitutional questions
here.
I think we all understand them.
Great. Okay. Thank you.
Thank you, Warren. Thank you for your submission and for being our last submitter
for today on the bill. We really appreciate you joining us.
Members, we'll be moving to the private-
See you, thanks
... sitting next. Thank you.
Bye-bye.